<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first part of the disquisition of truth, concerning political affaires Handled in two seuerall sections. The first whereof (by way of certaine questions probleme-wise propounded and answered) consisteth of foureteene chapters. Written by Henry Wright.</title>
            <author>Wright, Henry, fl. 1616.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15753</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26024</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120336</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855535</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855535</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21030</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15753)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21030)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1056:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first part of the disquisition of truth, concerning political affaires Handled in two seuerall sections. The first whereof (by way of certaine questions probleme-wise propounded and answered) consisteth of foureteene chapters. Written by Henry Wright.</title>
                  <author>Wright, Henry, fl. 1616.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 90, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>No more published.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Variant: title page lacks comma after "truth".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Political science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21030:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21030:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FIRST PART OF THE DISQVISITION OF TRVTH, CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CERNING POLITI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CAL AFFAIRES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>HANDLED</hi> In two ſeuerall Sections.</p>
            <p>The firſt whereof (by way of <hi>certaine queſtions probleme-wiſe</hi> propounded and anſwered) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of foureteene Chapters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by</hi> Henry Wright.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by NICHOLAS OKHS. 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21030:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21030:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, SIR <hi>JOHN JOLLES,</hi> Knight, Lord Maior of the Citie of LONDON. <hi>AND</hi> To the Right Worſhipfull the <hi>reſt of the Aldermen his</hi> Brethren, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable &amp; Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I very well know, that no man (almoſt) in handling any politique diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, could euer ſatisfie the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch as were skilfull, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull
<pb facs="tcp:21030:3"/> in the exerciſing, acting, and managing of ſuch affaires: the one, becauſe they could not vnderſtand: the other, for that they were (moſt what) too curious, neuer regarding any thing more, then the vſe thereof for ſeruing the time preſent: yet for the great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect I haue euer borne to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Citie of</hi> London <hi>(wherein I haue had the moſt part of my liuing and abiding,) and (in particular) to your Honour, and Worſhips the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy gouernours therof (whom I know to be iudicious, yet free from curioſity) I haue aduentured to propound to the world my priuate conceipts touching that ſubiect. May it pleaſe your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Worſhips therefore (till bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter grow) to accept theſe firſt fruits of my barren-braine, and by your fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb facs="tcp:21030:3"/> approuing of them, to protect &amp; defend them againſt the ſnarlings of blacke-mouth'd</hi> Momiſts, <hi>who are euer more ready to carpe at other mens writings, then to amend them, or to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any of their owne once to view the light. The matter I borrowed (as you may perceiue) out of the beſt and moſt approued Authours and Hiſtoriogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers: the forme, frame and diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the worke is mine owne, which (ſuch as it is) together with my beſt ſeruices, I commend to your Honour and Worſhips, and your ſelues to the grace of God, and ſo reſt,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By your Honour, and Worſhips euer ready to be commanded, Henry Wright.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:21030:4"/>
               <item>SECT. 1. CHAP. 4. <hi>Of a Kingdome: How it may be got, how kept, how it may be increaſed, how made laſting and durable; and laſtly, how it may bee loſt, or ouer-throwne, by hatred, contempt, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>SECT. 1. CHAP. 5. <hi>Of Councell, Councellors, and the chooſing of them: Of running middle courſes. The great good which redoundeth to a Prince being well-aduiſed, and how he may diſcerne good counſel from bad aduice.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>SECT. 1. CHAP. 6. <hi>Of Example: the vſe and abuſe thereof in a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>SECT. 1. CHAP. 7. <hi>Of wits, manners, and diſpoſitions of diuers Countries, Nations, and Cities, as well free as ſeruile.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>SECT. 1. CHAP. 8. <hi>Of benefits, and when to be beſtowed: of ingratitude, and how a friend may bee purchaſed, that a man may truſt to.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>SECT. 1. CHAP. 9. <hi>Of eſtimation and credit: of authoritie publique and priuate: of Seueritie, ſtrictneſſe of gouernement, Conſtancie, Pietie and Prouidence.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>SECT. 1. CHAP. 10. <hi>Of glory and renowne, the deſire thereof, profitable to</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21030:4"/> 
                  <hi>the Common-wealth. Of power and greatneſſe, and the acquiring thereof. Of ambition and vnlawfull deſire of reigning. Of eminent places, and their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing free (for the moſt part) from practiſes of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>SECT. 1. CHAP. 11 <hi>Of Studies, diſpoſitions, &amp;c. and whence the diuerſity thereof may proceed. Of learning, &amp;c. how neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for a Prince. Of intelligence, and the vſe and benefit thereof.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>SECT. 1. CHAP. 12. <hi>Of peace, and the conditions thereof. Of the ſtate and affaires of Princes. Of Embaſſages, Embaſſadours, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>SECT. 1. CHAP. 13. <hi>Of diſcord and faction, whereof they take their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and of the nouriſhing, or not nouriſhing of them in a common-wealth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>SECT. 1. CHAP. 14. <hi>Of Sedition, mutinie, and defection of the greateſt part of the people in a State, and of ſtanding N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trall, or part-taking.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div n="sources" type="list">
            <pb facs="tcp:21030:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21030:5"/>
            <head>The chiefe Authors whom I haue followed in compiling of this <hi>worke, Alphabetically ſet downe.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>A</head>
               <item>AVguſtine.</item>
               <item>Ariſtotle.</item>
               <item>Amianus.</item>
               <item>Attius.</item>
               <item>Aulus Politicus.</item>
               <item>Ariſtophanes.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B</head>
               <item>The Bible.</item>
               <item>Petrus Bembus.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C</head>
               <item>Quintus Curtius.</item>
               <item>Philippus Cominaeus.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:21030:6"/>
               <item>Capitolinus.</item>
               <item>Marcus Tullius Cicero.</item>
               <item>Cladianus.</item>
               <item>Philippus Camerarius.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>Dant an Italian Poet.</item>
               <item>Dio Caſsius.</item>
               <item>Diodorus Siculus.</item>
               <item>Demoſthenes.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>Euripides.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>Valerius Flaccus.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>Franciſcus Guicardinus.</item>
               <item>Aulus Gellius.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>Horatius.</item>
               <item>Herodotus.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>Iuuenall.</item>
               <item>Ioſephus.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:21030:6"/>
               <head>L</head>
               <item>Lactantius.</item>
               <item>Lucretius.</item>
               <item>Lucanus.</item>
               <item>Titus Liuius.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>Machiavell.</item>
               <item>Valerius Maximus.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O</head>
               <item>Ouidius.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P</head>
               <item>Plaro.</item>
               <item>Plutarchus.</item>
               <item>Phauorinus, Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus.</item>
               <item>Polybius.</item>
               <item>Plautus.</item>
               <item>Plinius.</item>
               <item>Pindarus.</item>
               <item>Pacuvius.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Q</head>
               <item>Quintilianus.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:21030:7"/>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>Henricus Ranzovius.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>Saluſtius.</item>
               <item>Stobaeus,</item>
               <item>Seneca,</item>
               <item>Suetonius,</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T</head>
               <item>Tholozanus,</item>
               <item>Thucidides,</item>
               <item>Cornelius Tacitus,</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V</head>
               <item>Velleius,</item>
               <item>Vegetius,</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>X</head>
               <item>Xenophon,</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Z</head>
               <item>Zimera Problem.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21030:7"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> THE FIRST PART OF THE DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>QVISITION OF TRVTH, Concerning Politicall Affaires.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>SECT. I. CAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Religion, and the force thereof: whereupon, and how it commeth to paſſe that there be ſuch, and ſo many, diuerſities, and differences, of Opinions, concerning the ſame.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may bee demanded wherefore the wiſeſt</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Licurgus. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon. Epaminon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, Numa, Xe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophon.</note> Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuers <hi>did euer concluſionally determine, that the care of</hi> Religion, <hi>and all holy things ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto the</hi> Prince?</p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>As it becauſe they thought it fit, that that which was <note n="b" place="margin">Diogenes apud Stobaeum.</note> beſt, and moſt worthy to bee had in honour, ſhould bee honoured of the beſt, and him who bare the chiefeſt rule in the Monarchy, or State? Or was
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21030:8"/> it rather, becauſe they wiſely conſidered, that <note n="c" place="margin">Xenophon Paedia Cyri. l. 8.</note> if their Subiects feared God, they would bee the more loath to do any thing which might redound to the hurt of one another, or attempt any thing againſt the Prince? Or was it not for theſe cauſes alone, but rather likewiſe, <note n="d" place="margin">Ariſt. Rhet. ad Alex.</note> for the augmenting and enlarging of their Empire and Dominions, as though the Diuine Powers were more prone, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious, and fauourable, towards thoſe that ſerue them, then vnto any others? Or to conclude, was it for the generall good of a Common-wealth, as a certaine <note n="e" place="margin">Lactantius de ira Cap. 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Diuine plainely proteſted, who held that <hi>Religion,</hi> and the <hi>Feare of God,</hi> were the ſureſt bands for conſeruing of Humane Society?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, how farre a Prince ought to take care of matters concerning Religion?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>OVght hee (as ſome do thinke) to take care for the examination of the truth or falſhood of that Religion which hee profeſſeth, and in all Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall matters to take vpon him to bee chiefe Iudge and Determiner of them, according to his owne municipall Lawes? Or ought hee rather (as others imagine) to bee a defender onely of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which formerly hath beene receiued, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards is propounded or obtruded vnto him?</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">The opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and States not ſubiect to the Pope.</note> This latter may be thought an vniuſt limitation, that any Prince, or State, ſhould bee ſo curbed: and as touching the former, <note n="g" place="margin">The opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church of Rome and her adh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rents.</note> others thinke that a Prince hath no free power, or authority, to conſtitute or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21030:8"/> determine Eccleſiaſticall buſineſſe, but that by bare permiſſion onely, hee may haue a meere inſpection into them: Which monſtrous Opinion, in a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe (almoſt ready to come forth) I haue reſuted: Euidently prouing that the Church, being a part of the State, it cannot bee without apparant danger to the ſame, to admit of forraigne Iuriſdiction in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging matters Eccleſiaſticall, but that ſuch affaires ought alwaies to bee ordered by thoſe who beare the Soueraignety, or ſome other, by their appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, within the ſame State.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may bee further demanded, wherefore the</hi> 
                     <note n="h" place="margin">Liu. lib. 7. hiſt. Rom.</note> 
                     <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes alwaies confeſſed and acknowledged that they were more obliged and indebted to</hi> Numa <hi>then to</hi> Romulus.</p>
                  <p>THis queſtion <hi>(Right Honourable)</hi> out of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes owne Hiſtory is thus reſolued: Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that <hi>Romulus</hi> (though founder of their Citty) left little or nothing vnto them, but their names to be called Romanes: But <hi>Numa</hi> (being the chiefe bringer in of Religion) perpetuated the ſame, and ſeemed to giue vnto them their very eſſence and being, and (as it were) to cauſe the proſperous ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of their State. For <hi>Romulus</hi> (ſaith the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) brought in the forme of a Common wealth, which was likely not to be durable, but might end with himſelfe: But his Succeſſor <hi>Numa,</hi> vpon the bringing in the continuall practiſe and exerciſe of Religion, did in ſuch wiſe forme and frame the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21030:9"/> Common-wealth, that though himſelfe ſhould ſhortly die, yet there was left an euident meane and way to make it durable for many ages.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To the ſame purpoſe it may be demanded, wherefore the</hi> 
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Liu. lib. 10. Hiſt. Rom.</note> 
                     <hi>Romanes did make more account of Religion then all other Nations?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>VVAs it becauſe they plainely ſaw, that the ſetling Religion in the State, was the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt prop they could rely vpon, for the vpholding, conſeruing, and perpetuating of their Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and that it would ſerue moſt fitly for the bringing in of Military Diſcipline, and Armes, to which they were moſt addicted, and without which they iudged their State could not ſtand? Or was it rather, for that they vnder this pretence (as thoſe who knew how to (make vſe of Religion) did practiſe it ore fortunately, and with better ſucceſſe then others, to retaine and keepe thoſe which were good in their allegeance and obedience, and to curbe and reſtraine thoſe who were ill diſpoſed from commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting euill, or perſiſting and continuing in their lewd courſes: as likewiſe to <note n="k" place="margin">Liu. lib. 3. Circa legem Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentillam.</note> pacifie the ſeditious, <note n="l" place="margin">Liu. lib. 3. circa creationem tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulorum plebis conſulari digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate.</note> reconcile ſuch Subiects as were iuſtly offended and grieued, with the Rulers and the gouernment, <note n="m" place="margin">Liu. lib. 5.</note> retaine their Military Diſcipline, and keep their Souldiers in good order, <note n="n" place="margin">Liu. lib. 10.</note> get credite and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to their Commanders: enterpriſe warres, and to bring them to a happy end?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:21030:9"/>
                  <head>5</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Againe, it may bee demanded to the ſame purpoſe, wherefore the</hi> Romanes, <hi>euen in their greateſt ſtreights and difficulties did rather vſe the pretext and colour of religion, to expedite and helpe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, then any other meanes whatſoeuer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>WAs it becauſe <note n="o" place="margin">Franciſe. Guicciardin.</note> they were perſwaded that the Common-people did rather iudge by the ſhadowes then the ſubſtances of things? Or was it not for that cauſe alone, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for that they found by experience, that men are more throughly moued, and thinke themſelues faſter tyed vpon an <note n="p" place="margin">Liu. lib. 3.</note> oath taken (which hath his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendancie vpon Religion) then by any Lawes or Statutes whatſoeuer?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded wherefore in former times men (generally) were more religious then they are in theſe dayes?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>WAs it becauſe that in thoſe elder times there was not that contempt of <hi>Religion,</hi> and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of God &amp; his ſeruice, as is now in theſe moderne dayes? Or was it rather, becauſe in thoſe more happy times, it was held altogether vnlawfull for any man to make what conſtruction he liſt of an oath when hee had taken it, and thereout to frame rules of liuing to himſelfe, according to his owne liking; but to faſhion his life and manners rather to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21030:10"/> ſuch lawes as were giuen, and impoſed vpon him to obſerue?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may finally be demanded, wherefore (ſeeing there is but one truth) there are at this day ſo many and ſundry opinions about Religion, euen among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans themſelues.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it becauſe the Clergie themſelues in diuers poynts diſagree, being diſtracted into factions, and writing and diſputing one againſt another; which the rude and ignorant multitude once ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, do thereby take vpon them to diſpute of <hi>Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,</hi> to eſtabliſh their fond and fooliſh opinions in matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> which in no wiſe belonged vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them to meddle withall? Or may it bee, for that ſometime yong Schollers, either in yeares, learning or diſcretion taking vpon them to preach, teach, or write, doe propound falſe or vnſound <hi>Doctrine</hi> to the people: whoſe corrupt opinions once ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broach (as though it were a ſhame for them to change them vpon more mature deliberation into better) do continually beſtirre themſelues, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy their wits, rather to confirme, then amend their errors? Or is this the reaſon rather, for that the followers of any Sect whatſoeuer, ſtudy to tread in their firſt Teachers ſteps, and obſerue ſuch cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and cuſtomes as formerly haue beene preſcribed vnto them?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21030:10"/>
               <head>SECT. I. CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the beſt forme of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may bee demanded, wherefore according to many mens opinions, the Monarchy, or ſole rule of one, ought to be preferred before other formes of gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>S it becauſe that <note n="a" place="margin">Cic. de legibus lib. 3. Iuſtinus H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtoricus lib. 1 in initio.</note> 
                     <hi>Monarchy</hi> is the moſt ancient kinde of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, ſeeing that the name of <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Empire</hi> was firſt in the world? Or is it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this kinde of gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment beſt agreeth to <note n="b" place="margin">Salust in Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolis.</note> nature, as is to be ſeene by all, or the moſt of all other creatures, in whom this image and ſhadow of one to rule ouer the reſt may plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare? Or is it becauſe it is moſt agreeable to <note n="c" place="margin">Tacit. 1. Annal</note> reaſon, that the body of an Empire being but one, ſhould likewiſe be ſwayed by the diſcretion of one ſole Ruler? Or is this rather the reaſon, becauſe that neither in a <note n="d" place="margin">Tacit. 4. Annal</note> popular eſtate, where many gouerne, nor in an <hi>Ariſtocracie,</hi> where a few ſway the ſcepter, there can be poſsible any long concord and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t among them? Or is it becauſe that both in <note n="e" place="margin">Tacit. 1. Annal Liu. lib. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocracies</hi> and <hi>Ariſtocracies</hi> it hath bin euer obſerued, <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:21030:11"/> euer great ſtore of good wits, which may bee fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and accomodated to all times and occaſions, better then other formes of gouernement? Or might this rather bee their reaſon, becauſe they obſerued that this forme of gouernement was not ſo ſubiect to <note n="n" place="margin">Ariſt. Polit. 5.</note> alteration, or to grow into tyranny? For to ſpeake as they would haue the thing to be, <note n="o" place="margin">The opinion of <hi>Machiauel, lib.</hi> 1. Diſputat. Cap. 5.</note> though theſe few of the <hi>Clariſsimi</hi> who ſway the gouernement, be naturally ambitious; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding when they ſee and conſider that all the authoritie is in their owne hands, and by reaſon thereof that they ſurpaſſe and excell the reſt of their people, they content themſelues (for the moſt part) with this prerogatiue, and ſo raiſe no tumults, or ſtirre vp any troubles whereby the Common-wealth might bee vexed or diſquieted for their ambitious humors.</p>
                  <p>And thus (Right Honorable) you ſee how that as euery one moſt fancied and affected this, or that kinde of gouernement: ſo they yeelded rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for the maintaining of their opinions? Wherein (in my conceit) they haue miſt the Cuſhion, and vpon good grounds (as I hope) I may argue againſt them all. And thus for Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſake I reaſon againſt their Monarchy.</p>
                  <p>Euery Monarch is either tied to rule, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the lawes of the kingdome hee poſſeſſeth, or he is not; If he be not bound, then all men will confeſſe with me, that that Monarchy may eaſily degenerate, and grow into tyranny. But if the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch bee tied to obſerue lawes, nothing letteth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21030:11"/> (notwithſtanding) but that forme of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth may not bee durable, eſpecially when the kingdome commeth by ſucceſſion. <note n="p" place="margin">Dantes Poeta Ital<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> For very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome falleth it out, that to a wiſe and godly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a Sonne of that ſtampe, and endowed with like vertues, ſhould ſucceed. Now, whenas by the peruerſe, careleſſe, or bad carriage of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch toward his people, the manners of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects are once corrupted, it muſt of neceſſitie fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that either the lawes are of ſmall force, or none at all. And ſo farewell to that forme of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment.</p>
                  <p>Againſt their <hi>Democracie,</hi> I this auerre, or (ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) finally determine, That if any good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels or Decrees come from the people, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from them rather by meere chance, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally, then for any prime or principall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the Councellers. For the people being driuen by ſome extreame neceſsity, to runne ſuch and ſuch courſes, or put in practiſe thoſe or theſe counſels, or being furthered by ſome memorable accident falling out in the nicke (as we ſay) may oftentimes decree things well and wiſely, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is impoſsible for them ſo to doe? For they know not (for the moſt part) what they would haue, they aske what they know not, and when they haue obtained what they asked, by and by they ſpurne, kicke at it, and deſpiſe it: ſo that the prouerbe in them, and of them, is true, and euer will bee verified; <hi>The people is a beaſt of many heads, wauering and enuious.</hi> So that I may very ſafely
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21030:12"/> conclude, that this forme of gouernment is worſt of all.</p>
                  <p>Againſt the <hi>State Ariſtocraticall,</hi> I this affirme, that experience hath made it manifeſt to the world, that thoſe, who for a while haue iuſtly and vprightly gouerned the Common-wealth, not long after haue abuſed their power and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the gathering of riches, and getting poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of lands into their hands, inſomuch that they haue growne ambitious, earneſtly thirſting after priuate reuenge, and the fulfilling of their owne filthy luſts and appetites, as appeared plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the <hi>Ariſtocracie</hi> of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> when after they grew weary to be gouerned by Conſuls, and had ſet vp the <hi>Decemvirate,</hi> in the beginning of the ſecond yeare of their gouernment, they were inforced to change that ſtate into a <hi>Democracie,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Decemviri</hi> ruled ſo villanouſly. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, it is recorded by antiquitie, that the ſonnes of vertuous parents, who were, and did ſucceede in diuers gouernements, became extreame inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, common letchers, and ſpend-thrifts of thoſe patrimonies which their carefull parents had left vnto them: Vpon which grounds I conclude, That the <hi>Ariſtocraticall</hi> gouernment cannot ſtand long firme, and ſtable, much leſſe to bee perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and durable.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe things then being, as I haue ſaid, and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that euery forme of gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is ſo ſubiect to change &amp; alteration, it were welworth the labour to</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21030:12"/> 
                     <hi>make a true Diſquiſition of this nice point, to wit, what forme of gouernment were fitteſt for euery Kingdome and Country, whereby the welfare thereof might bee procured and continued.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TO determine this queſtion <hi>(Right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble)</hi> were a very hard taske to be vndertaken and performed of any man, yet becauſe I haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vpon to diſcourſe of this ſubiect, I will in briefe ſhow your Lordſhip my opinion therein.</p>
                  <p>And firſt, I am verily perſwaded, that this, or that forme of gouernement, whether already eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, or to be brought in, and eſtabliſhed, in any Kingdome or Country, doth chiefly depend vpon the nature and diſpoſition of that Kingdome or Country, into which it hath bene already, or is to be brought: For it would be a very hard matter to bring a free forme of gouernment into that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, who haue bene vſed to liue vnder a Monarch, as contrariwiſe, to reduce that people, to liue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the obedience and command of one abſolute Ruler, who haue vſed to liue free of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, &amp; to bee gouerned by their owne Lawes. The Eaſterne Countries not enduring to brooke the <hi>Ariſtocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall</hi> or <hi>Democraticall</hi> State, were euer deuoted to liue vnder one ſole <hi>Monarch.</hi> On the other ſide, no forme of gouernment would pleaſe the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> and <hi>Heluetians</hi> (whom at this day wee call <hi>Switzers)</hi> but a <hi>Democracy:</hi> None the <hi>Lacedaemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> but an <hi>Ariſtocracy.</hi> The <hi>Syracuſians</hi> affected a tyranicall forme of gouernement: Neither
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21030:13"/> could any of theſe people euer bee perſwaded to forſake that forme of gouernment which they had once choſen: Nay, which is more, they did with ſuch deadly and implacable hatred, proſecute all thoſe who erected, or ſet vp any other kinds of <hi>Policies</hi> to bee gouerned, and to gouerne by, that whereſoeuer, and whenſoeuer, they became Conquerours, they altered and abrogated, that forme of Gouernement, and brought in their owne forme.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, I vtterly deny all right formes of Common-wealthes, as the <hi>Monarchy, Ariſtocracy,</hi> and <hi>Democracy,</hi> to bee abſolute and perfect: much leſſe do I hold that any goodneſſe can be in a <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranie, Oligarchy,</hi> or <hi>Ochlocracy;</hi> For theſe laſt rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by reaſon of the multitude of euils which accompany them, are of, and in themſelues al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies euill, the Magiſtrates neuer regarding the common-good but their owne ends: The former likewiſe, although in themſelues they are good (for that in all of them, the chiefe good of the Common-wealth, or State, either is, or ought to be ſought) yet accidentally, they many times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come euill; as well for that they laſt not long, as that they ſo eaſily degenerate.</p>
                  <p>To conclude therefore, I hold that forme of Common-wealth to bee beſt, which is compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the temper of all theſe, or at leaſtwiſe is ſo mixed of a <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Ariſtocracy,</hi> that one (indeed) for the Maieſty of the State ſhould bee the chiefe Commander, but his power ſhould be
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21030:13"/> gouerned, and his Councels ordered by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees and wiſedome of the Senate: For by this meanes, the Prince ſhould retaine his ſplendor and dignity, the Senate their power and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the people their lawfull liberty.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>SECT. I. CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Prince, Court, and Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, &amp;c.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may bee demanded why priuate men, can neuer well and rightly iudge of the affaires of Princes?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>S it becauſe they exactly <note n="a" place="margin">Guicchardine.</note> know not the matters of State, the ends of Princes, or how farre this, or that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, effected, or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, doth concerne them? Or may this rather bee the reaſon that <note n="b" place="margin">Idem.</note> foraſmuch as the counſels, purpoſes, and deſignes of Princes, differ ſo farre from the drifts and courſes of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate men, it is impoſſible that the ſelfe-ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects ſhould be auaileable to them both? For it (moſt what) ſo falleth out, that although matters of State, determinations of buſineſſes, and the commodities or diſcommodities which may be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21030:14"/> expected to ariſe thereof, ſhould be knowne as well to priuate men, as to Princes themſelues, their applications, cenſures, and iudgements, notwithſtanding touching the premiſſes, would be diuers, as their firſt ends and intentions were, which they had propounded to themſelues.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the next place it may bee demanded, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as wee commonly reade in Hiſtories, as out of</hi> Tacitus <hi>and others, that that man, whoſe aide and helpe a Prince hath made vſe of bring him to the Crowne, within a while after is neither liked nor loued of that Prince, but either is fed with the ſmoake of innouation, or made ſhorter by the head?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it becauſe that ſome Princes being naturally ſuſpicious, do eſteeme the faith of thoſe to be fickle to them, which they haue proued to haue beene to the damage of others? Or is not that the reaſon, but this rather, that the very ſight of them whoſe helpe they haue vſed to their riſing, groweth idious vnto them, for that it ſeemeth to vp-braide them with the baſeneſſe of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer meane fortunes? Or may it not be ſo neither, but for that it is <note n="c" place="margin">Philipus Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaeus.</note> grieuous vnto ſome Princes to remember that they owe any thing, or that they are any waies beholding to their Subiects?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, how that Prince, who hath bereaued another of his Kingdome,</hi>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21030:14"/> 
                     <hi>might behaue himſelfe to enioy his new-got Empire with ſafety?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>SShall hee effect this, if hee <note n="d" place="margin">This was the errour of <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius Tullius</hi> King of the Romanes, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>Tarquinius Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbus</hi> ſlew.</note> affect him whom he hath ſo ſpoyled, with new fauours and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites, endeuouring thereby to reconcile him, and binde him faſt vnto him? But it is to bee fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that old iniuries will hardly bee forgotten, by collating and beſtowing of new benefites vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wronged, eſpecially if the greatneſſe of the iniuries, exceede the rate of the benefites, as it falleth out commonly in the caſe of Kingdomes. Or ſhall he bring this about the rather, if he <note n="e" place="margin">This was the practiſe of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limus,</hi> the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Emperor, who being but a yonger bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, poyſoned <hi>Baiazet</hi> his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <hi>Corcut</hi> and <hi>Acomat</hi> his two brethren, &amp;c. So dealt <hi>Rich.</hi> the 3. with his two nephewes the ſonnes of <hi>Edward</hi> the 4. with the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> likewiſe, and others.</note> mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and kill, all thoſe whom he imagineth to ſtand in his way, or whom hee ſtandeth in doubt of, leaſt in time they may become his enemies? But if he take theſe courſes, he muſt needs fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome great miſchiefe; for he ſhall ingulfe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the vaſt Ocean of the peoples hatred, and thereby weaken his owne power againſt the time he ſhould haue moſt occaſion to vſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, why it ſo much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth Princes, and great men, to be cautelous that they do not iniury, or reproach any man?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it for that hee who is wronged of thoſe who are in <note n="f" place="margin">Philipus Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaeus.</note> eminent place, and authority, perceiuing himſelfe to bee daily and hourely ſhot at, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the ſame, grieueth the more therat, and ſo ſets vp his reſt to take a ſharp reuenge? Or ought
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21030:15"/> they to be cautelous for this cauſe likewiſe, <note n="g" place="margin">Cominaeus.</note> leaſt if the wronged hauing formerly retained vnto them, or made any dependency vpon them, ſhold vpon any truſt committed vnto him, pay them home, in neglecting, or vtterly ouerthrowing their chiefeſt buſineſſes?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, why it greatly impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a Prince, to bee Vertuous, Honourable of his word, iuſt, and of good Example among all men, as well Forreigners, as Domeſtiques?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it for that he may be thought vnfit <note n="h" place="margin">Xenophon in Paedia Cyri.</note> to gouern, who is not better euery way then thoſe who are to bee gouerned? Or is it not for that cauſe onely, but for that <note n="i" place="margin">Sen. 1. de Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentia.</note> his good name and fame likewiſe at home, and abroad is greatly blemiſhed and ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, if the courſe of his life and dealings bee not currant? Or ought hee to bee ſuch an one for the better ſtabliſhing of his Kingdome alſo? <note n="k" place="margin">Sen. Thieſt.</note> For where there is no ſhame, care of doing of <hi>Iuſtice, Sanctity, Piety,</hi> &amp; keeping of promiſe, thatkingdom muſt needs bee vnſtable, and the State tottering.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may be the ſame purpoſe further demanded, why a Prince ought to be iuſt, to make ſpeciall reckoning of the adminiſtration thereof equally to his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, ey, to do iuſtice vpon himſelfe, if hee deſire to be held for a good Prince?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it for that <note n="l" place="margin">Plato in Polit.</note> a Lawleſſe Principallity, and looſe gouernement is yrkſome to euery one (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21030:15"/> of the better ſort) ſo that they do not delight, or haue any deſire to liue vnder it? Or is it for that the conſtant and ſtrict obſeruation, and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Iuſtice, doth ſtabliſh and ſtrengthen a Kingdome, as the <note n="m" place="margin">Cic. Parad.</note> Oratour well perceiued, who ſaid that Iuſtice and Equity were the true conſeruators of Common-wealthes and Cities? Or is it not onely for that iuſtice doth ſtabliſh a Kingdome, but for that it doth truely make a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to be a Kingdome, giuing vnto it his very eſſence and being, whereby it is, that which it is? For take away Iuſtice, and what are Kingdomes but great Robberies? as well ſaid the <note n="n" place="margin">Auguſt. de Ciuil. Dei lib. 4.</note> learned Diuine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, why many Princes are very fearefull, ſuſpicious, and iealous of their eſtates?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it becauſe that <note n="o" place="margin">Attius.</note> Kingdomes are commonly ſubiect to treacheries? Or is this rather the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for that the <note n="p" place="margin">Sen. Oedip.</note> nature of moſt Princes is prone to feare, and be iealous of their Eſtates? as well ſaid the Poet, <note n="q" place="margin">Sen. in Agam.</note> Kingdomes and Mariages brooke no riuals.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, wherefore all credit, countenance, honors, and authority in Court, are for the moſt part ſlippery, and not to be truſted vnto?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>HAppeneth it thus by reaſon of the Fates vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty (as it pleaſeth the <note n="r" place="margin">Tacit. 3. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalium.</note> Hiſtorian to ſet
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21030:16"/> downe) who auerreth, that Court-fauours, euen by decree of the deſtinies, are not alwaies laſting? Or might this rather be the reaſon, for that <note n="ſ" place="margin">Tacit. 17. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalium.</note> Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers credites are (commonly) vpheld by others, and not by their owne ſtrengths? Or not ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but for that theſe things thus fall out through the fault of the Princes, their Maiſters, whom they ſerue, whoſe wils and pleaſures as they are <note n="t" place="margin">Saluſt. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurth.</note> vehement for the time, ſo they are very changeable, and oftentimes contrary to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seeing that the</hi> 
                     <note n="u" place="margin">Sen. in Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polito.</note> 
                     <hi>Court is ſo ſlippery a place, that a man ſhall hardly get faſt footing: It may fitly bee demanded, by what Compaſſe a Courtier ſhould ſaile, that hee may bee without all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſhipwracke, whereby either his life may bee hazarded, his goods diminiſhed, or his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour blemiſhed?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>SHall he attaine vnto thoſe ends, if he ſhow him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe dutifull, obſequious, and reſpectiue of his Prince, as it pleaſed the <note n="x" place="margin">Tacit. 1. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note> Hiſtorian to affirme? For by how much the ſeruant in the iudgement of his Maiſter, ſhall bee held more deſirous and ready to pleaſe him, then another ſhall; by ſo much the more hee ſhall bee aduanced to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and riches? Or may hee compaſſe his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires the better, if he be <note n="y" place="margin">The ſaying of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great.</note> ſeruiceable likewiſe, and not like the moathes, and caterpillars of the Court? Or may hee rather further his intents,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21030:16"/> if he be bold ſpirited alſo? For ſhamefaſtneſſe is an ill ſeruitour in a Princes Palace, as well ſaid the <note n="z" place="margin">Sen. in Hippol.</note> Poet. Or ſhall he be cautelous likewiſe, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king heed that whatſoeuer he well doth or perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, he do it as <note n="a" place="margin">Velleius. 11.</note> though he ſeemed not to do it, and without boaſting or bragging? Or (to auoid enuy) ſhall he learne to <note n="b" place="margin">Tacit. 16. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note> diſſemble, cloake, and obſcure his owne vertues, and proper gifts? Or ſhall hee, being any wayes aduanced by his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces fauours, like the Moone, <note n="c" place="margin">Tacit in Agric</note> acknowledge (of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes) that he hath receiued all the light of his glory, and grace of his riſing, from that Sunne his maiſter? Or ſhall hee ſtriue and endeuour to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come very <note n="d" place="margin">Sen. 11. de ira.</note> patient, and <note n="e" place="margin">Sen. Hippolit.</note> extreame wary like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe? He muſt be very patient, that he may beare iniuries the better, &amp; not flie out, or run into paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vpon euery croſſe he ſhall meet withall, or ſuch diſtaſtes as ſhall be giuen him. He muſt bee cautelous, leaſt he be taken in the traps of his fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned friends, or ſecret, or open profeſſed enemies.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, why it is better to liue with, and ſerue a prudent and wiſe Prince, then a fooliſh?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it becauſe that a <note n="f" place="margin">Philip. Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus. lib. 4.</note> fooliſh Prince being (for the moſt part) very ſuſpitious, thinketh that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of his ſeruants goeth about to deceiue him, which to an <hi>Honeſt</hi> minde muſt needes be a great erroſiue? Or is it for that a <note n="g" place="margin">Idem ibidem.</note> fooliſh Prince not vnderſtanding his owne affaires, cannot make
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21030:17"/> difference of good ſeruice from bad, whereupon it commeth to paſſe, that his loue is turned into hatred, and his hatred into loue in a moment? Or is it not for theſe reaſons onely, but for this like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that <note n="h" place="margin">Phil. Com. lib. 4.</note> thoſe ſeruants which liue vnder a wiſe Prince, haue moe meanes affoorded them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their maiſters fauour, if they once haue had it, or to recouer it if they haue loſt it, then it is poſſible they can haue, who liue vnder an Ideot, or fooliſh Prince? For no man almoſt dealeth in any thing with the Prince himſelfe, but with his <note n="i" place="margin">This was wel ſeene in the Duke of little <hi>Brittaine,</hi> who vſed onely <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Landoys.</hi>
                     </note> ſeruants, whom he changeth as often as he put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on a cleane ſhirt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To the ſame purpoſe it may further be demanded wherefore (notwithſtanding) many Courtiers haue rather choſen to liue in the Courts of ſome great Prince, though a foole, then in the Palace of a leſſe potent Prince, though neuer ſo wiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it becauſe that <note n="k" place="margin">Lucas de Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</note> it is true libertie (as ſome ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) to liue vnder the command of a potent Prince? Or is it rather, as others affirme, for that <note n="l" place="margin">Egiſippus cum alijs, vt refert Guic.</note> the ſeruitors ſeruices are graced and beautified by the greatneſſe and ſuper-eminent dignitie of their maiſters?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <head>13</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seeing that none are borne Artiſts it may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, what manner of Courtier is to be deemed and eſteemed to be the better Crafts-maiſter in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging affaires of State?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:21030:17"/>
                  <p>IS he the man who is <note n="m" place="margin">Guicchard.</note> furniſhed with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of diuers tongues, well ſeene in Hiſtories of the lawes of his owne and other Countries, that is religious, hath a quicke wit, a ripe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a fluent tongue, a graue ſtile, &amp; is an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent pen-man? Or is he rather to be ſo accounted, who is <note n="n" place="margin">Guic. &amp; Tacit 3. Annal.</note> ſmooth-tongued; gorgeouſly apparrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, a great feaſt-maker, an artificiall coſouner, a deepe diſſembler, a whoore-maiſter, tale-bearer, flatterer, a priuy-whiſperer, and one that is giuen to all kinde of villanie?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="section">
                  <head>14</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, what might bee the beſt meanes wherby Princes may free themſelues, from being abuſed by flatterie?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>MAy they effect this if they beware and take heed that they <note n="o" place="margin">Tholoz. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. lib. 22. cap. 8</note> grow not into contempt with their people? Or ſhall they bring their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe better about, if they ſit often in counſell, and touching thoſe things which they propound to be conſulted vpon, doe ſhew themſelues <note n="p" place="margin">Plut. Apotheg.</note> patient in hearing the truth, that their people may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that they will not be offended, if they freely ſpeake their mindes, and confidently deliuer that which is true? Or may this likewiſe further their intents, if vpon the <note n="q" place="margin">
                        <hi>Machiauel</hi> his doctrine in his Prince. <hi>Cap.</hi> 23.</note> perceiuing and finding out of ſome or other, who for ſome ſiniſter reſpects (though towards themſelues) haue held their peace, or forborne to ſpeake the truth, they do ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhew themſelues to be greatly offended with them, or ſeuerely puniſh them?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21030:18"/>
               <head>SECT. I. CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of a Kingdome: How it may be got, how kept, how it may be increaſed, how it may be made laſting or durable: And laſtly, how it may bee loſt, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-throwne by hatred, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, &amp;c.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may be demanded, by what wayes and meanes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Principalitie may be gotten, or conquered.</hi> 
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>S it to be atchieued by <note n="a" place="margin">Quintus Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius. lib. 6.</note> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Armes, as it happened to <hi>Alexander,</hi> when hee had ouer-throwne <hi>Darius</hi> at <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella?</hi> For after that victory, he neuer vſed in the full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>Aſia,</hi> or other king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, any other but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne forces, for the moſt part. Or is it rather to be gotten by an home-bred Army, ſeconded by the vertue and the manhood of the Leaders, and Captaines, as it fell to the lot of <note n="b" place="margin">Xenophon.</note> 
                     <hi>Cyrus, Romulus,</hi>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21030:18"/> and <hi>Theſeus?</hi> Or may it bee attained by forraigne force alſo, ſeconded by <hi>Fortunes</hi> fauours, as it happened to <hi>Francis Sfortia,</hi> and <hi>Borgia Caeſar?</hi> Or may it bee gotten by the putting in practiſe of ſome notorious and deſperate deſigne, as it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to <hi>Agathocles?</hi> Or may it be compaſſed by the fauour of the Citizens, as <hi>Nabides</hi> got his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the next place it may bee demanded, how any Principality being once gotten, may be ſafely kept.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>MAy this be effected if the Prince proue indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious, and accomodate himſelfe to make and take aduantage of ſuch accidents and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as time will continually affoord him, and in all other things to imitate and follow the ſteps of his Aunceſtors? Or may it be effected, if he neuer giue any offence to thoſe, whoſe helpe he vſed in getting his dominion, but ſatisfie them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their deſires and hopes (if it be poſſible) as they haue conceiued of their owne worths? Or may he this way rather attaine therunto, if finding treaſon intended againſt him, he ſhould moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely puniſh it, for terrour to the reſt? Or may it this way be effected, if vpon the obtaining of his dominion, he <note n="c" place="margin">The barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Turkes at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery change of Prince.</note> deſtroy all the bloud Royall, iſſues and allies, of the former Prince, and then obſerue the Countrey cuſtomes without changing their lawes? Or may this rather bee effected, if hee that hath once gotten the ſoueraignty, remoue his ſeat
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21030:19"/> thither, and make his continuall reſidence in his new dominion? Or may this yet rather bee effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, if the Prince ſend Colonies into his new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten kingdome, or maintaine garriſons both of horſe and foote, in the frontier townes? Or may hee better bring this to paſſe, if (after conqueſt made) dealing courteouſly with them, hee retire himſelfe, and accept of an annuall penſion, in the name of a tribute, leauing onely ſome ſmall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany behinde him, rather to nouriſh and encreaſe his ſubiects good opinion of him, then for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end or purpoſe? or may he effect this the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if he altogether ſhould change their lawes and cuſtomes, and tranſlate them to other remote pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the ſame kingdome, then thoſe which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they inhabited? or may this rather be the way to purchaſe the fauour and good opinion of the Senators, or commons, hauing them alwayes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to his fortunes, taking vpon him valiantly and couragiouſly to defend thoſe of his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, againſt the other faction? or were not this the better courſe, to ſtand vpon his owne guard, hauing an army euer in a readineſſe to chaſten his ſubiects if they ſhould rebel? Or finally, what if the <note n="d" place="margin">This did <hi>Crae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> among the <hi>Lidians,</hi> as <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lib.</hi> reporteth.</note> Conquerour ſhould diſpoyle the conquered of their weapons, and other meanes of defence or offence?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, how a new got King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome may be enlarged?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>SHall this be attained vnto, if the <note n="e" place="margin">This was the practiſe of the <hi>Romans</hi> in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</hi>
                     </note> Conquerour
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21030:19"/> ſhew himſelfe milde &amp; gentle to his new ſubiects, thereby to allure the hearts of the neighbour bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, to take a liking of his manner of gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Or may it rather be effected, if <note n="f" place="margin">This fell out in the <hi>Macedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie.</note> a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of wiſe and warlike Princes do ſtil ſucceed one another in the ſelfe-ſame gouernement? Or may this be better done, if the conqueror haue a great care that <hi>Military diſcipline</hi> be alwaies vſed within his territories? Or ſhould he rather go this way to worke, to <note n="g" place="margin">This &amp; ſuch like practiſes were the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes.</hi>
                     </note> demoliſh the walles of the neighbour Cities, and cauſe the inhabitants to remoue their dwellings into his territories? Or ſhall he friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inuite all ſtrangers to come into his domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, giuing them letters of ſafe conduct, and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them of their dwelling ſafely vnder his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection? Or ſhall he combine with diuers neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Cities, ioyning themſelues with them as aſſociats, ſo as the name of the Empire and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, as likewiſe the authoritie of leuying of warre, may euer remaine with him, and bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per vnto him? Or ſhall he make thoſe whom hee hath conquered to <note n="h" place="margin">Thus dealt the <hi>Spartans, Venetians</hi> and <hi>Florentius</hi> with them whom they conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> become vaſſals and ſlaues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him? Or might this be effected, if certaine Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties making <note n="i" place="margin">The practiſe of the <hi>Switzers</hi> at this day.</note> league among themſelues, that they will all be gouerned, and with equall digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and reſpect, ſhould draw in other Cities to affect that kind of gouernment, and ſo to ioyne in the ſame league and amitie with them?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, which might bee the beſt way to make a ſtate durable and laſting?</hi> 
                  </p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:21030:20"/>
                  <p>SHall this be brought to paſſe, if by lawes it bee prouided for, vnder paine Capitall, that <note n="k" place="margin">All theſe things were fore-ſeene by <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> the <hi>Laced. emonian</hi> Law-giuer.</note> no man ſhould affect the Gouernement? Or may it better bee effected, if the Prince being ſtrong of himſelfe, ſhall yet giue teſtimony to his neighbour Princes, that hee is not ambitious, nor ſeeketh by leuying of Armes, to enlarge his Dominions to any of their detriments? Or ſhall hee doe it yet the better, if by idleneſſe, and vaine pleaſures hee ſuffer not the mindes of his ſubiects to bee corrupted, or that they ſhould grow too much effeminate?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſidering that Kingdomes are ſtrengthened as well by awfull Armes, as bright ſhining</hi> Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, <hi>it may bee demanded, by what kinde of force a Kingdome may beſt bee preſerued, and made durable.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>SHall it bee made firme and ſtable by hauing an Armie euer in a readineſſe, rather to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend then defend, according to the counſell of the Emperour <hi>Seuerus;</hi> which he gaue to his ſons, <note n="l" place="margin">
                        <hi>Sic habetur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Dionem in vita eius.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Agree among your ſelues, enrich the Souldier, and contemne all others?</hi> Or ſhall this bee the better way to make it ſtable, if the Prince <note n="m" place="margin">So did the <hi>Florentines</hi> to keepe <hi>Piſa</hi> and <hi>Francis Sforeia</hi> to conſerue <hi>Millaine,</hi> but not to much purpoſe.</note> build many Forts, Towers, Citadels, Sconces, &amp;c. within his Territories?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seeing that hatred once conceiued againſt a Prince by his ſubiects, is the next way to bereaue him of his Crowne, it may bee demanded, how the</hi>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:21030:20"/> 
                     <hi>Prince may run into ſuch hatred, and what meanes hee might beſt vſe to auoid it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>MAy hee runne into this hatred by his owne <note n="n" place="margin">Mach. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. lib. 2.</note> boundleſſe ambition, ſeeking to bring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bondage, and the great deſires of his Cittizens to continue free? Or may hee come hated of his Subiects, by reaſon of <note n="o" place="margin">Mach. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. lib. 3. cap. 6.</note> the iniuries hee hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered them, either in ſeeking their liues, touching their honours, or preying vpon them for their ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches? Or rather may it this way come to paſſe that hee be hated, for that he hath <note n="p" place="margin">Cic. Phillip. 2.</note> giuen cauſe to the Subiects to feare him, leaſt he do them a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe? For, to feare, deſire of reuenge is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall companion. And this prouerbe is moſt true, whom a man feareth, him hee hateth; whom he hateth, he would gladly bee rid of? Or may this bee the reaſon hee runneth into ſuch hatred, for that hee is <note n="q" place="margin">Tholoz. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. lib. 22.</note> vitious; as cruell, couetous, ſacrili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may bee further demanded, how the inflicting of ſeuere puniſhments vpon offenders, may bee freed from hatred?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>SHall the Prince free himſelfe there-from, if hee bee <note n="r" place="margin">Sen. de Clem.</note> ſlow to puniſh delinquents, and thereby giue teſtimony to the world, that his intent is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to heale, and bind vp a ſoare, then to launch and make it bleed by the arme of Iuſtice? Or ſhall hee this way free himſelfe, if hee neuer puniſh,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21030:21"/> but <note n="ſ" place="margin">Sen. de Clem.</note> when the ſafety of the Common wealth cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vpon him ſo to do, or at leaſt his Subiects be ſo perſwaded? Or ſhall hee this way rather bee freed, if hee <note n="t" place="margin">Cic. 2. de Offic.</note> neuer exact to take puniſhment of delinquents in an angry moode? Or may he this way auoide his Subiects hatred, if hee <note n="u" place="margin">Sen. 1. de Clem.</note> ſhew no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> any ſignes of reioycing, when hee inflicteth pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment vpon offendours, as though he thirſted after bloud, or were delighted with the ſhedding of it? Or rather may this be his way, that when many haue offended, hee do not <note n="x" place="margin">Tacit. Agric.</note> now and then call them to account, as hee liſteth, holding them in a perpetuall feare, but take his aduantage againſt all, and puniſh all forthwith? Or rather by this way may he be freed therefrom, by not deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing any new kind of puniſhments, but inflicting thoſe which haue beene in vſe, according to old and ancient cuſtome of the Country? Or may he this way likewiſe free himſelfe, if hee be very ſparing in puniſhing of delinquents, and when he doth it, hee might bee thought to command it to bee inflicted againſt his will, but neuer to bee a ſpectator thereof? Or finally, may hee thus free himſelfe there-from, if to pleaſe his ſubiects, hee diuert the force of his fury another way, <note n="y" place="margin">Tacit. 13. Annal.</note> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſuch as haue beene his counſellours, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaders to wrong the Common-wealth, to taſte the cup of his choler, by inflicting ſeuere pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments vpon them, or deliuering them into the peoples hands to be tormented?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:21030:21"/>
                  <head>8</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded how a Prince may free himſelfe of that hatred which hee hath purchaſed, by vexing his Subiects with Impoſitions, Taxes, Tallages, &amp;c. which are commonly grieuous to them to beare?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>MAy this be done if the Prince perſwade the people <note n="z" place="margin">Tacit. 13. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note> that if they will liue in peace and out of danger, that it is altogether neceſſary they indure ſuch impoſitions, which if they ſhould not, it were impoſſible for them to liue in ſafety, or the State to bee durable? For <note n="a" place="margin">Tacit. 4. hiſt.</note> peace is not purchaſed but by Armes, nor Armes maintained but by Souldiers well paid, nor can the Souldier be paid without leuying of Subſidies? Or ſhall the Prince free himſelfe, if hee command the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers of ſuch Impoſitions, that they <note n="b" place="margin">Idem. Ibid.</note> neither by force, nor fraude, exact more of the Subiect, then anciently hath beene accuſtomed to be paid? Or ſhall hee rather this way auoide their hatred, if ſparingly, as iuſt occaſion inforceth him, hee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend and lay out ſuch treaſure, as hath beene leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Subſidies, that his Subiects may ſee and perceiue, that hee is but a Steward, for the good of the Common-wealth, and no riotous ſpender, or exhauſter of the treaſure ſo gathered: or that he hath any deſire to conuert any of it, to his owne vſe, or ends? Or ſhall hee thus rather free him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, by taking of a courſe, that <note n="c" place="margin">Plin. Paneg.</note> iuſt and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme contribution be made according to euery
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21030:22"/> mans ability, neuer by fauour ſparing one man, that the burthen may lye the heauier vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans ſhoulders?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, how, and by what meanes, a great and potent Subiect, may auoide and ſhunne, the hatred of his Prince?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>MAy this be effected, if this great Noble man make himſelfe firſt odious to the people? Or ſhall hee better effect it, if hee ſhew himſelfe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dutifull and obſequious to his Prince, praiſing all his good deeds, and ſayings, and craftily diſſembling whatſoeuer is bad in him? Or ſhall hee attaine therevnto, if hee <note n="d" place="margin">This was the practiſe of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipater,</hi> one of <hi>Alexanders</hi> Captaines, as <hi>Q. Curt.</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</note> neuer proiect to make himſelfe great, ſtrengthen himſelfe with friends, or ſeeke to bee maiſter of greater riches, then is conuenient for his eſtate? Or if fortune haue eaſt all theſe things vpon him, that hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge continually, that hee hath receiued, gained, and gotten them, by the grace and fauour of his Prince, whoſe they are, whenſoeuer he ſhall pleaſe to make vſe of them? Or ſhall hee this way auoide his Princes diſpleaſure, if he haue a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all care to <note n="e" place="margin">This was the practiſe of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab, Dauids</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</note> attempt or do nothing, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting with, or obtaining the conſent of his Prince, though otherwiſe hee were aſſured that hee could preuaile in his attempts, and that it would turne to the good of his Country? Or ſhall hee this way ſhunne it, if being for a certaine time made Deputy, Lieutenant General, or raiſed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21030:22"/> and euected to any other ſpeciall place and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, he <note n="f" place="margin">The praictſe of <hi>Antipater</hi> and <hi>Lucius Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cullus.</hi>
                     </note> forth-with at the end, and expiration of his time reſigne his office to his Princes hands, and in no wiſe ſeeme to be deſirous that it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed, or continued vnto him, leaſt hee ſhould ſeeme to be ſick of the ſwelling <hi>humours of Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> Or may hee this way auoide it, if hauing wonne, and prouing victor in diuers battels, hee impute the glory of his Conqueſts to the good fortune of his Prince, deſiring that the victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Army may now bee led by ſome other, whom the Prince ſhall thinke good of, and retiring, put himſelfe into his Princes protection, carrying himſelfe in a moderate faſhion, as free from pride and ambition? By this onely meanes a great Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, though ſuſpected and feared of his Prince, may ſo mollifie and lenifie his minde, that hee ſhall haue no cauſe to thinke ill of him, but ſhall make to himſelfe great and apparant reaſons to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him for his good ſeruices.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, why euery King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is ſo fickle and vnſtable? </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it becauſe that euery <note n="g" place="margin">Sen. Oedip. Idem. etiam Ep. xcij.</note> Principality is the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of Fortune, who can neuer be daunted, but challengeth the like priuiledge againſt Empires, as Emperours. Or may this bee the reaſon rather, becauſe it is expoſed to ſuch, and ſo many hatreds, as the Tragicall <note n="h" place="margin">Senec. Theb.</note> Poet ſung, The Maker of the world coupled theſe two together; <hi>Hatred</hi> and a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21030:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> Kingdome. Or may this be the cauſe, for that it is ſubiect to ſo many <note n="h" place="margin">Attius.</note> treaſons, treacheries, &amp;c. for there bee very many in a Kingdome which bee naught and vnfaithfull, few good?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To the ſame purpoſe it may bee demanded, why among the</hi> Grecians <hi>and</hi> Romanes, <note n="i" place="margin">Senec. Theb.</note> 
                     <hi>a Kingdom was ſo hatefull for the moſt part?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>DId this come to paſſe by reaſon of the <note n="k" place="margin">Idem Agam.</note> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and crooked diſpoſitions of their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who being (for the moſt part) licentiouſly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, thought it was a great pledge of their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and badge of their Royaltie, that it was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for them to do that which no body elſe might? Or being ſelfe-wild, or proud, <note n="l" place="margin">Idem in Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polito.</note> accounted it no leſſe diſhonour vnto them, to be drawne to yeeld to any thing (though neuer ſo iuſt) againſt their wils, then to be vanquiſhed in battell? Or is not the fault ſo much in the diſpoſitions &amp; wils of kings, as in the harſh <note n="m" place="margin">Soluſt. ad Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarem.</note> natures of the Subiects, being ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, refractary, and hardly wonne to yeeld due obedience? For no man willingly, would draw in another mans yoake.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seeing that authority is as it were the</hi> 
                     <note n="n" place="margin">Cicero pro Cluent.</note> 
                     <hi>ſpirit by which euery Common-wealth is gouerned, being flatly oppoſed to contempt, which may bee called the</hi> 
                     <note n="o" place="margin">Arist. 5. Poſit.</note> 
                     <hi>bane and deſtruction of all Kingdomes, it may be demanded, how a Prince may behaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that hee neither fall into contempt amongſt his owne Subiects, or forraigne States?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:21030:23"/>
                  <p>SHall he effect this, if the <note n="p" place="margin">Tacit. 11. hiſt.</note> faſhion of his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement proue not too remiſſe, and gentle, whereby he may be thought to be negligent in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering affaires of State? Or ſhall hee performe it the rather, if hee <note n="q" place="margin">Idem Ibidem.</note> ſhew no leuity in the forme of his gouernment, but conſtantly gouerne, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Lawes and Decrees of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth? Or ſhall he effect this likewiſe, if he ſhew himſelfe firme in his purpoſes, conſtant in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and that hee hath no <note n="r" place="margin">Idem Ibidem.</note> notable touch of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tability in his diſpoſition? Or ſhall hee bring this to paſſe, if (curiouſly) pondering things paſt, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending, and well weighing things preſent, and prouidently fore-ſeeing things to come, hee doe timouſly conſult, and determine, to beſtow ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours on <note n="ſ" place="margin">Idem Ibidem.</note> ſuch men, as for their worth haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued; not vpon euery fawning and obſequious fauourite, or ſuch as can purchaſe them with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney? Or may hee doe this the better, if Fortune proue a mother vnto him, and not a ſtep-dame? Or ſhall he finally effect this likewiſe, if he firſt <note n="t" place="margin">Tacit. 15. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe his owne luſts, and inordinate affections, giuing thereby his Subiects examples to follow him in the like, and cauſing Forreigners to admire him therefore?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <head>13</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may be further demanded how an Empire, or Kingdome may be finally loſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>COmmeth it thus to paſſe, by a kind of a <note n="u" place="margin">Tholoz. lib. 22 de repub.</note> fatall neceſſity, when this or that State hath come</p>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:21030:24"/>
                  <p>a Councellour to a Prince to be skilfull of the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of other nations, and to be a ſtranger in his owne Common-wealth: or ſhall he compaſſe this the better if he make choyce of <note n="e" place="margin">Saluſt. Catil.</note> graue and auncient men, as alſo of ſuch as haue <note n="f" place="margin">Idem in frag.</note> beene toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and tried with the variety of Fortune, hauing therby learned to carry themſelues both in weale &amp; woe? Or laſtly, ſhall the Prince neuer admit of any for his Councellours, but ſuch as <note n="g" place="margin">Plin. Paneg.</note> generally are accounted wiſe and vertuous? For particular men may deceiue and bee deceiued, but no one man can deceiue all men, neither hath any man bene deceiued of all men.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Againe it may further be demanded, how a Prince may behaue himſelfe in his Conſultations, that he may grow wiſe thereby, and ſo be accounted?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>SHall hee effect this, if hauing wiſe Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours to aduiſe him, hee apt and accomodate himſelfe to follow their directions, and what they haue maturely deliberated and concluded vpon, hee forth with put in practiſe and execution? Or ſhall hee better effect this, if ſitting in Councell himſelfe, he propound, and heare them with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and diſcretion debate the matter, and <note n="h" place="margin">Capitolinus de Marco Antonio.</note> neuer ſeeme to be angry, or ſtriue to maiſter and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule their opinions, though they determine cleane contrarie to his owne humours, minde and deſire? Or ſhall he rather bring this to paſſe, if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to <note n="i" place="margin">Vigetius lib. 3.</note> containe himſelfe, and keepe cloſe his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21030:24"/> owne Councels and intentions, he doe (indeede) propound what ought to bee done to all, or the moſt of his Counſell to conſider of; but what he will doe, to communicate it with very few, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther none, but aduiſe onely with himſelfe? Or ſhal he rather performe this, if he grant free liberty of ſpeach, neither doe too much affect thoſe <note n="k" place="margin">Quint. Curt. lib. 8.</note> ſoft and ſilken words of the Court, which his flatterers will be ready to claw him withall; knowing that they will pleaſe his humours? Or finally ſhall hee effect this, if with indifferencie, and all alike e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality, he heare euery mans opinion, neuer <note n="l" place="margin">Thucid. lib 3.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding any councelling well, leaſt for the hope of gaine, they might vpon ſiniſter reſpects (at any time) decline from the right, nor <note n="m" place="margin">Quint. Curt. lib. 3.</note> puniſh any (though they ſhould counſell ill (ſo they do it not of maliciouſneſſe) for ſo he ſhall euer want Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours, if it be dangerous to giue counſell?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, why it is ſo exceeding auaileable to a Prince, to haue his counſels and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations kept ſecret?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it becauſe that if they were <note n="n" place="margin">Guicchardine</note> knowne, they might be preuented and hindered? Or is it for this reſpect rather, becauſe his honour and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation both at home and abroad, is thereby much increaſed and augmented? Or not ſo much for the former reaſons neither, but for that if his determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations were once knowne, <note n="o" place="margin">Idem.</note> many men pricked forward with enuy, would detract from his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21030:25"/> blaming him that hee put not his intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſooner in execution, though hee could not (happily) finde fit opportunity ſeruing thereunto?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, what courſe a Prince might beſt take, that hee might not erre in his Conſultations?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>SHall he performe this, if hee fully vnderſtand the <note n="p" place="margin">Tholoz. lib. 24.</note> nature of the buſineſſe, which is to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberated vpon? Or ſhall he do it the better, if vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding the matter, whereof to conſult, hee <note n="q" place="margin">Guicchardine</note> conſtantly determine with himſelfe rather to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect (cautelouſly) the extreames, and finall ends of buſineſſes, then to regard middle courſes, much leſſe to run them? Or ſhall hee alſo effect this, if hee obſerue and marke how <note n="r" place="margin">Idem.</note> wiſely and prudently his aduerſarie (if any he haue) behaueth himſelfe in thoſe things, which concerne his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, profit or ſafety? Or ſhall he rather accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate and apply his counſels to the nature, manners and condition of his aduerſarie, and by that meanes learne out and expiſcate what might be likely that he will attempt againſt him? Or ſhall hee compaſſe theſe things the better, if in all his counſels and deliberations concerning the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, he rather propound to himſelfe how the honor, dignitie and ſplendor thereof may bee augmented, then what profit might thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound vnto it?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:21030:25"/>
                  <head>5</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, what is chiefly requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of Senators, that they may giue wholeſome counſell. </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>MAy they effect this, if they be <note n="ſ" place="margin">Plin. Panet.</note> men fearing God, making his plaine &amp; euen lawes the ſtrict and ſtraight rule of their conſulations? For ſeeing it is <note n="t" place="margin">Tholoz. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>4.</note> God alone, which ſuſtaineth and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth Common-wealths, it were very fit that he ſhould be made the chiefe head, and director of the counſels thereof. Or may they do it the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if ſtanding for the <note n="u" place="margin">Tacit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. Hist.</note> libertie of themſelues, and the Common-wealth, they do ſtoutly and coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly, not faintly and fearefully pronounce and deliuer their mindes and opinions, leaſt they might rather be thought to runne with the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of the Prince, then with him, or the good of the Common-wealth? Or may they alſo effect this, if they ſhew themſelues <note n="x" place="margin">Tacit. 3. Hiſt.</note> modeſt, and of a quiet diſpoſition? Or may they likewiſe effect it the better, if they can <note n="y" place="margin">Quint. Curt. lib. 4.</note> keepe their owne counſels? For it is very certaine that no great matter can be looked for at his hands, who will vent what hee ſhould hold in? Or finally, may this better be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, if choyce be made of ſuch Councellors which haue <note n="z" place="margin">Tholoz. lib. 24. de repub.</note> no particular intereſt in thoſe things which are to be conſulted vpon? For no man in his owne cauſe, can ſpeake, thinke, or iudge vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly, becauſe euery man therin will be partiall.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſidering that middle courſes (for the moſt part)</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:21030:26"/> 
                     <hi>proue vnfortunate, it may be demanded why not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the running of a middle courſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing propounded by ſome one or other in publike de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberations, it is (moſt what) embraced, followed, and put in execution?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>COmmeth it to paſſe through the ill <note n="a" place="margin">Fran. Guich.</note> diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and worſe affection of ſome addicted to faction and oppoſition, who perceiuing that their owne conceits cannot paſſe currant, had rather giue way to, and allow of that which is worſe, not extreame (leaſt hee ſhould ſeeme to oppoſe) but different in a leſſe diſtance, that thereby they may ſeeme to haue (in part) aſſented?</p>
                  <p>Or is it not for this reaſon alone, but for that likewiſe the other aduiſers, <note n="b" place="margin">Idem.</note> leaſt they ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe ſome prime-man, who hath propounded a middle courſe of proceedings, will likewiſe run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with him, and approue of his deuiſe? Or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is this the reaſon why ſuch middle courſes are by ſome no ſooner propounded then appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, becauſe (for the moſt part) prouident and wary, eſpecially auncient and aged Statiſts, do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue of that courſe which they imagine to bee leaſt violent and dangerous, and incline to the meane, as being the ſweeter and more paſſable without noyſe or Nuiſſance.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seeing that the cloſe minds, wils and ends of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours be ſtrange, diuers, and for ſiniſter reſpects, priuately kept to themſelues, for (oftentimes) vpon</hi>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:21030:26"/> 
                     <hi>pounding of matters to bee conſulted vpon,</hi> 
                     <note n="c" place="margin">This was the practiſe of <hi>Torlton</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> againſt <hi>Edward</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, by whoſe aduice his ſon was ſent into <hi>France,</hi> who ioyning with his mother &amp; <hi>Mortimer,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the head and Captaine of the Rebels againſt his owne father.</note> 
                     <hi>one thing is ſpoken, another thought and meant, whereby the mindes and opinions (onely) of others may be diſcouered; it may here be demanded, how a Prince may iudge whether his Councellours aduiſe him well or no?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>SHall hee know this by the <note n="d" place="margin">Mach. in Prin.</note> diſpoſition of the Councellor? For he that more reſpecteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe then his Prince, &amp; in the carriage of any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter regards his owne priuate more then the good of the Common-wealth, as long as hee beareth this minde, he can neuer proue a faithfull Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour, nor one whom the Prince or State may truſt or rely vpon. Or ſhall hee vnderſtand this by the <note n="e" place="margin">Tholoz. lib. 24.</note> frequent vſe &amp; experience he hath had of his Councellours in the like buſineſſes falling out ill, or well? Or ſhall he rather come to the knowledge hereof by making an <note n="f" place="margin">Idem ibidem.</note> exact: ſearch and diſpoſition how matters are carried and diſpoſed of within his owne territories? Or ſhall he rather come to this knowledge by the frequent reading of Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries? or by the apprehending or comprehending of theſe two Principles, <hi>What is Profitable, What is Honeſt.</hi> Which two indeed are the bounds and grounds of truth, and of that worthy wiſedome and iudgement which ought to be in a Senator.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:21030:27"/>
               <head>SECT. I. CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Example, the vſe and abuſe thereof in a Common-wealth.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may bee demanded, why ſubiects (for the moſt part) <note n="a" place="margin">Claudian.</note> frame &amp; conforme themſelues to the faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Princes?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>S it for that both the <note n="b" place="margin">Plin. Paneg.</note> eyes of the minde, and the body, (for the moſt part) looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and ſtand (as it were) at gaze at greatneſſe and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minencie, tending and ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the whole man to <hi>dance</hi> as they <hi>pipe?</hi> Or is it becauſe <note n="c" place="margin">Tacit. 3. Annal</note> Examples vrge and enforce more then Lawes can do, ſeeing it is the nature of man, rather to be led of his owne accord; then to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled? Or is it rather for that <note n="d" place="margin">Quintilian decl. 4.</note> Example in Princes is a kind of ſecret law? For it fareth and falleth out thus (for the moſt part) with their acts, that what they doe, they euen ſeeme to command it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Againe it may be demanded, why in reforming of a Common-wealth, the producing of examples of the</hi>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:21030:27"/> 
                     <hi>moſt famous and illuſtrious men, for vertue in the ſame do very much auaile?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it becauſe that ſuch men being compelled by no Lawes, yet of their owne accord, and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, acting, exerciſing, and exhibiting, ſingular and rare examples of vertue, do excite and ſtirre vp ſuch as bee good, to follow them, and thoſe which are bad, they doe either make them a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or diſcourage them from going on in their lewdneſſe? Or is it rather for this, that when by long proceſſe of time, there hath bene no exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary puniſhment inflicted vpon offenders, men grow regardleſſe of Lawes, and the number of delinquents ſo increaſe, that the Magiſtrate is afraid to puniſh them? Then one <hi>Manlius Torqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> to puniſh his owne ſonne; or a <hi>Quintus Fabius</hi> to bee accuſed and condemned for ioyning bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell with the enemy, without the <hi>Dictators</hi> leaue; and ſuch examples, do much bridle and repreſſe other mens inſolencies.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, why hee that iudgeth by examples is commonly deceiued?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it for that <note n="c" place="margin">Franciſo. Guicch.</note> all the ſelfe-ſame reaſons and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances in the like actions, do ſeldome, or neuer concurre, and meete againe? Or is it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <note n="f" place="margin">Idem.</note> like actions are not alwaies gouerned with the like wiſedome and diſcretion? Or may this bee the reaſon rather, becauſe <note n="g" place="margin">Idem.</note> Fortune at all
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21030:28"/> times, playeth not her part alike, but now and then faileth her fauorites?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>SECT. I. CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Wits, Manners, and Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: of diuers Cities, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and Nations, as well free as ſeruile.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may bee demanded what kind of wits, may bee termed the beſt wits.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ay ſuch bee counted for the beſt, which are <note n="a" place="margin">Guicch.</note> more ſtirring, ſharpe, and acute, fiery and ſubtile, then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary? But theſe noble and excellent wits (for the moſt part) do proue very croſſe, and are oftentimes the cauſe of much diſquietneſſe, turmoile, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to him who is indued therewith. Or may thoſe rather bee taken for the beſt, which though <note n="b" place="margin">Idem.</note> more blunt, yet are more certaine and laſting, and (for the moſt part) are more fortunate then the other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, why in one and the</hi>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:21030:28"/> 
                     <hi>ſelfe-ſame Citie, there may be found many diſtinct families, whoſe manners and conditions are parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular to themſelues; as wee read amongſt the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, that the</hi> Manlij <hi>were euer ſterne and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere, the</hi> Publicolae <hi>courteous and gentle, the</hi> Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pij <hi>proud and ambitious, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>COmmeth this to paſſe, by reaſon of the diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of their temperatures? But that (as it may bee thought) might be changed and altred, by the variety of Marriages. Or may this rather be the cauſe, for that euery Family hath a peculiar man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of bringing vp their children? for this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly holdeth true, <note n="c" place="margin">Mach. Diſput. de Repub. lib. 3. cap. 46.</note> whatſoeuer manners and opinions, are inſtilled into the minds of youth in their infancy, they will hardly or neuer bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, but continue with them euen to their old age.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may bee further demanded, why</hi> 
                     <note n="d" place="margin">
                        <hi>Liu.</hi> in his bookes affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth this of the <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>diuers Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, at the firſt aſſault, or onſet giuen, ſeeme to bee magnanimious, and very fierce and forward to the battell, but within a while after doe grow very fearefull, and turne Cowards?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>MAy the cauſe conſiſt in any peculiar affect in their natures? But it is poſſible that <note n="e" place="margin">Mach. diſput. Cap. 36.</note> nature from day to day, may bee cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and amended? Or might this rather bee the reaſon, that ſuch Nations being <note n="f" place="margin">Idem Ibidem.</note> without order or exerciſe of Military Diſcipline, are not ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21030:29"/> with ſuch ordinary manhood, as may eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh their hearts and mindes, making them to conceiue an aſſured hope of victory, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if they be not vanquiſhers in the firſt aſſault, they ſtraight waies quit the field? And this (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der correction) I take to be the true reaſon of their fearefulneſſe and running away.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, wherefore diuers men (euen lewd perſons) hauing many times occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions offered them, to commit ſome memorable and notable villany, notwithſtanding (for the moſt part) they dare not attempt it, or put it in practiſe, and execution?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it for that they are afraid leaſt they ſhould <note n="g" place="margin">Mach. diſp. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. cap. 27.</note> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre the note of infamy? But the greatneſſe of the thing, might (happily) couer the badneſſe of the fact, and likewiſe protect the party from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Or do they abſtaine from perpetrating and committing ſuch horrtble villany, by reaſon of their <note n="h" place="margin">Idem Ibidem.</note> owne in-bred goodneſſe, or nice touch of their conſcience? But ſuch godly and holy moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons do neuer enter into the hearts of ſuch lewd loſſels. Or may this rather bee the reaſon, for that by nature, it is not affoorded to the moſt men, to be <note n="i" place="margin">Idem Ibidem.</note> abſolutely euill, or perfectly good?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, why there ſhould bee ſuch, and ſo great difficulty, in chaunging or amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding old cuſtomes, though moſt men (conuicted ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21030:29"/> in their conſciences by euident truth) ſhould confeſſe they were altogether vnprofitable, and dangerous to the Common-wealth to continue them?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>MAy this bee the reaſon, for that although ſome good Citizens, or Patriots, foreſeeing the danger, do perſwade the change thereof, yet they ſhould not be able fully to turne the peoples mindes, by reaſon of others oppoſitions? Or may this rather be the cauſe, for that moſt men ſtand ſo affected, and affectionated, to their auncient courſe of liuing, that they would not willingly depart there-from? Or may this bee the reaſon of the difficulty of amending euill cuſtomes, for that there is euer a want of proportionable meanes agreeable to the Lawes, to bring that buſineſſe about, ſo that they muſt bee driuen to flie to new courſes altogether, which ſeldome proue fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate? Or may this rather bee the reaſon, for that if ſome few, or any one man, ſhould go about to change the forme of gouernement, it ſhould bee neceſſary for him, firſt by force to inuade the State, and then to ſeize the liberties thereof into his hands, which might bee thought not to bee the part of a good man, and therefore hee will rather deſiſt from his purpoſe, then do his Citti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens ſo much good? Or may this bee a further rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for that the moſt men are perſwaded, that there can ſcarcely be that man found, who hauing once brought a State vnder ſubiection, by ill
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21030:30"/> meanes, would afterwards vſe that power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority which hee had ſo ill gotten, to the benefite and good of the people?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>SECT. I. CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Benefites, and when to bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed: Of Ingratitude, and how a friend may be purchaſed that a man may truſt vnto.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may bee demanded when Benefites are to bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon a man?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>RE they to bee collated vpon him <note n="a" place="margin">Mach. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſp. lib. primo, cap. 23.</note> iuſt at that time, when the beſtower of them is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled ſo to doe, as needing the preſent help of ſuch a man, or for ſome priuate end to himſelfe beſt knowne? But this manner of giuing ſhould ſeeme to be very extrauagant, and diſtaſtefull, to the receiuer, as thinking that they were collated vpon him by reaſon of the parties neceſſity, which once ſerued, he would neuer conferre more vpon him. Or are they not ſo to bee collated vpon any man, but <note n="b" place="margin">Idem Ibidem.</note> timouſly rather, before hee which may
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21030:30"/> haue need of them, ſhall haue occaſion to vſe them, or the Collator thereof the perſon?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, wherefore they who haue</hi> 
                     <note n="c" place="margin">As <hi>Charond as</hi> amongſt the <hi>AEginenſians, The miſtocles</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians; Camil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Scipio, &amp;c.</hi> among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, or put to death.</note> beſt deſerued of a Common-wealth are (of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes) worſt recompenced and requited?</p>
                  <p>IS this the reaſon, for that <note n="d" place="margin">Pindarus.</note> there is nothing leſſe laſting then the very name of a Benefite? Or is this rather the cauſe, for that it is <note n="c" place="margin">This was proper to the <hi>Athenians</hi> and <hi>Lacedaemonians.</hi>
                     </note> appropriate and peculiar to certaine Common-wealths, ſo to enuy thoſe which excell in vertue and goodneſſe, as they themſelues being not able to follow and imitate them therein, ſeeke to ſpoile them of their gouernement and Empire? Or may this rather be the reaſon, that ſome <note n="f" place="margin">Philip. Comin.</note> ſtanding too much vpon their owne merites, haue borne themſelues too proudly againſt tje State, or their owne ſociety? Or might this likewiſe bee the cauſe, for that thoſe, who either by their rare exploits, or cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ambition, creepe into the fauour of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at home, and hunt after renowne and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion abroad, may ſeeme to dimme the glory of their Princes, who greatly deſire to be accounted well-deſeruing of their owne people, as thoſe to whom it more properly belongeth, and therefore they muſt needs oppoſe ſuch, and grow in diſtaſte of them? Or is it for that all men generally by their owne corrupt nature, are leſſe prone, prompt, and ready to requite a good turne, then to reuenge an iniury? Or may this rather bee the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21030:31"/> reaſon for that the Prince, or <note n="g" place="margin">Vpon this very conceite the <hi>Venetians</hi> put to death <hi>Lauderanus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied a commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by his owne authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; as <hi>Petrus Bem bus</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in his <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian</hi> Hiſtory.</note> State, groweth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuſpicion of ſuch kinde of men, leaſt they ſhould affect innouation, or ſeeke to tyranniſe?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, why kindneſſes, and good will, are oftentimes requited with ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and vnthankfulneſſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it becauſe that he which neither can, nor hath any deſire to remunerate him, to whom hee is ſo much indebted, will either forget them, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade himſelfe, and the world, that no ſuch kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes were offered vnto him, or receiued by him? Or may this be the reaſon, that thoſe men, who haue beene (as it were) driuen, and by fatall neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity compelled to receiue kindneſſe of other men, ſhould afterwards grow aſhamed of it, that they ſhould bee thought to haue had neede of ſuch meanes?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seeing that no man can deny, but that the vſe of friends is ſuch, and ſo great, that many times a man may bee driuen to relye his whole eſtate thereupon; It may bee demanded, how a man may bee aſcertained, that hee hath purchaſed a true friend?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>SHall hee giue confidence to him, whom hee hath <note n="h" place="margin">Guicchardine.</note> bound by grace and benefites? Or ſhall hee truſt him, who hath any waies neede of his helpe? Or ſhall hee rather repoſe his confidence
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21030:31"/> in him who is bound <note n="i" place="margin">Pindarus.</note> vnto him, by hauing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall profite and ſhare in any buſineſſe, which they ſhall ioyntly attempt and obtaine?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>SECT. I. CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Eſtimation and Credit, of Authoritie, publique and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, Seueritie, ſtrictneſſe of Gouernment, Conſtancie, Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and Prouidence.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seing Authoritie is the prop of kingdomes, and that it is of the moſt men confeſſed, that the maieſty of an Empire conſiſteth in the ſplendor, grace, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence thereof: it may bee demanded, how a Prince might beget ſuch a reuerent opinion of himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his ſubiects, &amp; forreigners likewiſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he might become both admired and feared?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Hall he effect this, if he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute ſuch a forme of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, which is <note n="a" place="margin">Cicero pro mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</note> ſeuere, conſtant, and ſtrict, bearing an hard ouer thoſe whom he ruleth? Or ſhall he attaine therunto the better, if hauing <note n="b" place="margin">Mach. Prin. &amp; Tholoz.</note> home-bred ſtrength &amp; forces, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21030:32"/> keepe them about him, and haue them in a readineſſe? Or if he be deſtitute of ſuch forces, doe ſtraight wayes take a courſe to prouide them elſe-where? Or ſhall he compaſſe this the rather, if he excell other Princes in the <note n="c" place="margin">Claudian. 3.</note> integrity and ſoundneſſe of his manners, faſhions, and good conditions? Or ſhall he yet the better effect this, if hee delight ſtill <note n="d" place="margin">So <hi>Ferdinand</hi> King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the 5. King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> grew fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous.</note> to be in action, and grow fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for well performing of what hee vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth? Or ſhall he likewiſe obtaine his purpoſe, if in caſes of difference betwixt Princes, he <note n="e" place="margin">Mach. Prin. Cap. 21.</note> cut off all reſpects of <hi>Newtrality,</hi> and declare himſelfe for one of them? Or ſhall he this way come to his ends, if he giue this teſtimony to the world, that hee is a louer of vertue, honouring all excellent men, of what ſort and Art ſoeuer? Or finally, ſhall he this way compaſſe his deſires, if hee giue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement and hope to his ſubiects whom hee gouerneth, that they ſhall liue quietly vnder his protection, and peaceably go about their affaires and buſineſſes, in what kinde ſoeuer they ſhall traffique or deale?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, wherefore it concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a Prince ſo deeply to be highly eſteemed both at home and abroade?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it for that <note n="f" place="margin">Fran. Guicch.</note> eſtimation and authority once loſt (which may eaſily be done) can hardly or neuer be recouered againe? Or is it for that <note n="g" place="margin">Idem.</note> eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and authority in martiall affaires, is of ſo
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21030:32"/> great conſequence, that the effecting of any bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe of import, doth wholly ſeeme to depend thereupon? Or may it be for this reaſon rather, that it ſhall be much more difficult for him whoſe credit and eſtimation beginneth to decay to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelfe and his eſtate from the leaſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, then for him who keepeth vp his eſtimation, and hath it imprinted in the hearts of his ſubiects or ſouldiers, to effect great matters, though his meanes be weaker? Or may it be for this reaſon likewiſe, for that it ſometimes importeth a Prince to ſet his authority vpon the tentors, and ſtretch it beyond his ability for the effecting and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of ſome great enterpriſe? Now a Prince ſhall neuer bring this to paſſe, vnleſſe his ſubiects and ſouldiers be perſwaded, that his power, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and eſtimation, is greater then (indeed) it is; but if they be thereof once perſwaded, he ſhall haue that done readily, freely, and of their owne accords, which otherwiſe he ſhould neuer haue had granted, much leſſe extorted from them againſt their wils.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, how a Prince may compaſſe it to be feared of his ſubiects, and withall get himſelfe great reputation thereby?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>SHall he doe this, if he vſe them <note n="h" place="margin">Fran. Guich.</note> rigorouſly, and oftentimes inflict ſeuere puniſhments vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them? For they will eaſily be brought to ſtand in feare of him, whom they know both can and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21030:33"/> will correct them, and bring them into order, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if they perceiue him by his naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, to be thereunto addicted. Or ſhall hee finally effect this the rather, if he neuer vſe a ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <note n="i" place="margin">Guicchardine.</note> medicine, then the nature of the diſeaſe, or ſtrength of his ſicke ſubiects are able to beare?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, how a ſubiect may gaine himſelfe reputation with the common people?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>SHall he doe this, if he be <note n="k" place="margin">Mach. diſp. cap. 34.</note> deſcended of noble Aunceſtors, who haue approued themſelues braue and excellent men in the carriage of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and managing of great actions? Or ſhall he do this the rather, if he betake himſelfe to a wiſe and well ſetled courſe of life, conuerſing with none (as neere as he can) but with excellent men, and ſuch are vertuous? Or ſhall he yet effect this the better, if in his younger yeares he ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme any thing, either publickly or priuately, which in it ſelfe is memorable, and withall is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt? Or ſhall he attaine thereunto likewiſe, if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing truſted with the <note n="l" place="margin">Mach. Prin. cap. 21.</note> managing of publique af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of his Countrey, he diſcharge himſelfe well thereof, hauing rather an eye that his actions may redound to the good of the common-wealth, then to his owne or other mens priuate, how neere or deere ſoeuer they may be vnto him, or himſelfe to himſelfe?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, wherefore the Romans</hi>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:21030:33"/> 
                     <hi>thought it neceſſary, that their Generals of the field managing Armes amongſt forraigne Nations, ſhould haue free libertie to diſpoſe of thoſe affaires according to their owne beſt liking.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>WAs it for that the <note n="m" place="margin">Mach. diſp. lib. 2. Cap. 33.</note> Senate did well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that if they commanded their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals ſhould attempt nothing without their directions, aduice and priuities, it would be the next way to make them looſe, idle, and leſſe circumſpect in exerciſing their charge and office? Or was this rather the reaſon, for that they were perſwaded, <note n="n" place="margin">Idem Ibidem.</note> that the fortune of the warres were doubtfull, and that ſometimes ſuddaine accidents might fall out, which might very much either ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance and further their deſignes, or greatly hurt them; which occaſions (as they rightly deemed) he onely could take, vnderſtand, and make aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of, who ſhould bee preſent when they were offered?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, how the Authoritie and eſtimation of a Prince may bee made famous, if he ſhould carry a ſtrict hand ouer his ſubiects, in ruling and gouerning them?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>SHould hee compaſſe his ends, if hee alone ſhould <note n="o" place="margin">Tacit. 2. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Liu. etiam lib. 9.</note> retaine and keepe all the maine offices and buſineſſes of the crowne in his owne hands, ſo that all men ſhould be enforced to looke vpon, and vnto him, as of whom onely they were to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21030:34"/> all things which might doe them good? Or ſhall hee yet compaſſe his deſignes, if hee neuer prorogue, or continue any too long in an office, (eſpecially in militarie affaires) leaſt his ſubſtitute growing too proud, ſhould work any thing which might turne to his preiudice?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, why this or that Prince his gouernement is counted ſharpe and ſeuere; when the rule of others is thought to bee very gentle and eaſie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>MAy this be the reaſon, for that <note n="p" place="margin">Mach. diſp. lib 3. cap. 22.</note> ſome au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere man comming to the gouernement, doth wiſh, and hath (as it were) a longing deſire to haue all men like himſelfe? Or may this rather be the reaſon, for that ſuch a man comming to ſway the ſtate, is commonly a valiant man, and therefore commanding great and difficult enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes to be vndertaken by his ſubiects, vſeth ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſeueritie, whereby thoſe things may be put in execution, according as they were comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, wherefore it ſhould bee needfull that that gouernment ſhould be ſtrict and ſeuere, which ſhould beget authoritie and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to a Prince?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>MAy this bee the reaſon, for that Ienitie (for the moſt part) cauſeth contempt, and that
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21030:34"/> in any corruption of manners it is neceſſary the <note n="q" place="margin">Saluſt. Lepid.</note> ſubiect doe ſtand in awe, or be made to ſtand in awe of his Prince? Or may this rather bee the cauſe, for that <note n="r" place="margin">Cicero pro Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</note> clemencie and remiſſneſſe opens the maine gappe to offending, when men are perſwaded that they ſhall ſcape vnpuniſhed? For <note n="s" place="margin">Sen. 1 de Clem.</note> who will feare him who alwayes keepeth his ſword faſt locked in the feabbard, or for a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <note n="t" place="margin">Cic. 1. in Catil.</note> idleneſſe ſuffereth the edge of his authoritie to be blunted? Or may this rather be the reaſon, for that the common people are euery way better ordered, being compelled to do their duties, and by keeping them in feare, then if all the clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, courteous intreatie, and demeanor of the Prince ſhould be affoorded them?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, why the conſtant kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of one manner and forme of gouernment, muſt needes much auaile to make a Prince much e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>MAy this bee the reaſon, for that (as all <note n="u" place="margin">Tholoz.</note> innouation in a State is dangerous) the Prince ſhall be put in fault, and greatly blamed, if vpon changing any thing in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, it ſhould not well ſucceed and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per? Or may this rather be the reaſon, for that <note n="x" place="margin">Thucid. lib. 6.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience hath taught vs, that thoſe States and Common-wealths are beſt gouerned, which affect the leaſt alteration of old cuſtomes and manners, though they be not all of the beſt?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:21030:35"/>
                  <head>10</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, why a godly and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Prince is held in great honour and eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the people?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it for that <note n="y" place="margin">Tacit. 2. Annal</note> 
                     <hi>Pietie</hi> and <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> euen of it ſelfe is venerable, making Princes to ſeeme like Gods among their people? Or may this rather be the reaſon, for that the people are perſwaded that the <note n="z" place="margin">
                        <hi>Liuy</hi> in his firſt book ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mention, that <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the Nymph <hi>Egeria &amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> Prince will not attempt or goe about any enterpriſes, but ſuch wherein he ſhall bee ſeconded by the helpe of <hi>Heauen?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:21030:35"/>
               <head>SECT. I. CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Glory and Renowne, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thereof profitable to the Common-wealth: Of Power and Greatneſſe, and the acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thereof. Of Ambition and vnlawfull deſire of raigning: Of eminent Citties, and their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing free, for the moſt part, from practiſes of Treaſons, Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Inſurrections, Mutinie, &amp;c.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may bee demanded, what might bee the reaſon, that the vehement deſire and thirſt after glory and renowne, hath alwaies beene praiſe-worthy, and held profitable for the Common-wealth, whereas the leaſt deſire of raigning, in any great Subiect, hath beene condemned on all hands, and euer thought to bee dangerous and hurtfull to the State?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>S it becauſe <note n="a" place="margin">Fran. Guicch.</note> the hunting after honour and renowne, eleuateth and raiſeth a mans thoughts, and exciteth to noble and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21030:36"/> actions? Whereas contrary wiſe the ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and boundleſſe deſire of ruling, prouoketh a man to propound to himſelfe dangerous cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and to runne them though it be to his owne vndoing? Or may it bee for this reaſon likewiſe, for that hee which is of an <note n="b" place="margin">Idem.</note> ambitious and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent ſpirit, regardeth neither right or wrong, of Soueraigne or Subiect, but vpon the leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit to compaſſe his vnlawfull deſires, engageth himſelfe in factions, brawles, and quarrels, filling all mens hearts with feare, and diſturbing the quiet of the State ſo farre, that as much as in him lyeth, he will rather hazard the ſafety of it, then deſiſt from his barbarous enterpriſe? Whereas hee who is onely deſirous of honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne, neither feareth dangers, nor attempteth or alloweth of any lewd courſes, whereby hee, or his, might bee branded with the note of infamy, or digrace?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, how</hi> 
                     <note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>Liuy lib.</hi> 2. Potency is the high-way to gaine authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> 
                     <hi>potency and greatneſſe may bee acquired, whereby the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a Prince may bee made more illuſtrious and reſplendant?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it to bee purchaſed with money, to whom <note n="d" place="margin">Ariſt. Rhet. II. cap. 16. &amp; horat. Serm. 11.</note> all things do ſtoope? Or is it to bee acquired by Armes rather? for this is an infallible rule, that large Empire and Dominion, is not gotten, kept, or maintained by <note n="e" place="margin">Tacit. 15. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note> idleneſſe, but by the vſe and exerciſe of Armes, and Millitary Diſcipline? Or is
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21030:36"/> it not gotten by theſe meanes alone, but by <note n="f" place="margin">Tacit. 11. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note> firme counſell, and wary circumſpection alſo? Or may it be attained vnto, by making <note n="g" place="margin">Ariſt. Rhet. ad Alex Cap. Vltim.</note> firme leagues, and ſure peace with forraigne Princes? Or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, may it bee gotten by the <note n="h" place="margin">Quint. Curt. lib. 8.</note> benefite of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, who (moſt what) doth maruailouſly fauour and aduance ſome ſpeciall ſorts of men?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, what might bee the reaſon that thoſe men who are ambitious, and haue an itching deſire to bee inueſted with the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of States, if they once bee euected to ſome eminent place in the Common-wealth,</hi> 
                     <note n="i" place="margin">So it fared with <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Gaunt</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocke</hi> Duke of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors of <hi>Rich.</hi> the 2. And with <hi>Rich.</hi> the 3. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector of <hi>Edw.</hi> the 5. &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>they are neuer contented, but ſtriue and endeuour to riſe higher and higher, and if once they can ſurprize the State, they wil rather die, then come afterwards to leade a priuate life?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>COmmeth it thus to paſſe, for that all <note n="k" place="margin">Mach. diſp. lib. 1. cap. 37.</note> men euen by nature, are apt and prone to deſire great matters, though they bee not ſo fitted and accommodated in themſelues, to obtaine and keepe them? Now where the deſire is more then the ability to get, the minde can neuer be at quiet, or contented with thoſe things which already it doth enioy. Or is it for that <note n="l" place="margin">Guicchardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> Ambition of it ſelfe blindeth the eyes of men, perſwading them that their merites and deſerts are greater then (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) they bee, and thereupon they affect and attempt ſtrange matters, and run head-ſtrong courſes to their owne deſtructions oftentimes?
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21030:37"/> Or may this bee the reaſon, for that hee who once hath had his temples circled with a Crowne, can neuer after brooke a priuate life, becauſe Kings and Kingdomes, are euer to bee thought and beleeued to exceed proportion?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, what man may rightly be cenſured and deemed to be ambitious?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS hee ſo to bee deemed and taken, who vnder <note n="m" place="margin">Aul. Pol.</note> pretence of amplyfying and enlarging the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity Royall; will ſeeke to dominere ouer others, and rule all things according to his owne luſts? without cauſe or reaſon, changing the auncient Officers (though neuer ſo honeſt) at his will and pleaſure, and ſuffecting others into their places, whom hee well knoweth to be of his owne facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and (when time ſhall ſerue) will fauour his party? Or may hee likewiſe be thought ambitious who with great <note n="n" place="margin">Tholoz. lib. 22</note> gifts, large promiſes, and all kind and friendly Offices, ſeeketh to conciliate and get the fauour and good will of the people, whereby hee may be one ſtep higher to his riſing?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, why all the Arts, cunning and practiſes, by which ambitious men ſtudy to climbe to the height of greatneſſe, are kept ſo ſecret, that they hardly or neuer burſt out, or come to be knowne, till they haue obtained what they ſought for?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:21030:37"/>
                  <p>COmmeth it ſo to paſſe, for that <note n="o" place="margin">Mach. diſp. lib. prim. Cap. 46.</note> men do not by and by (and as it were vpon the ſodaine) but by degrees grow ambitious; whoſe progreſſes being not obſerued (except of ſome few) they may more eaſily deceiue and blind mens eyes? Or may this rather be the reaſon, for that the ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous do alwaies <note n="p" place="margin">Idem. Ibidem.</note> vſe ſome honeſt pretext whereby they may compaſſe their deſignes, as though all their actions did tend and bend to theſe ends, leaſt the Common-wealth (forſooth) or them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſhould be wronged, when the truth is, that they ſtriue to get the garland, that thereby they may both oppreſſe others, and the weale Publick?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, how, and by what ſafe meanes it may be prouided for, that a man ſhall not grow too ambitious and inſolent in a State, or if hee ſhould, how his inſolency may bee repreſſed, and nipt in the head, whilſt it is yet in the bud?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>MAy this bee effected, if there ſhould neuer way be giuen, or meanes affoorded, to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate or erect any ſuch office, or eminent dignity in the Common-wealth, out of the which the State might haue cauſe to feare, leaſt in proceſſe of time, Tyranny might take her firſt riſing, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning there-from? Or may it rather thus bee compaſſed, if the State take heed, and with wary circumſpection prouide, <note n="q" place="margin">Ariſtophanes in Ranis.</note> that they neuer foſter, cheriſh, orbring vp, any Lyons Whelpe, much
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21030:38"/> leſſe the Lyon himſelfe, within their Territo ries? Or may it thus likewiſe be done, if ſuch wormes, and <note n="r" place="margin">Tholoz. lib. 22.</note> moaths, which breed of too much moiſture, and are wont to conſume thoſe things whereof they had their beginnings, bee choked or ſhaken off, before they come to any great bigneſſe, or turne the whole Subſtance of that they feed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, into their owne? Or may it thus likewiſe bee brought to paſſe, if heed be taken, that if by the heate of the boſome of the Common-wealth, there bee hatched and nouriſhed any dangerous ſerpent, it bee <note n="ſ" place="margin">The errour of the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and <hi>Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues,</hi> that they would not doe after this Counſell.</note> timouſly expoſed to the cold (which is the onely way to kill it) yet neuer ſuffer it to hiſſe other where in a place more commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, leaſt by ſucking out the poyſon thereof, there might follow a deeper ſtinging? Or may this alſo be effected, if heed be taken that the <note n="t" place="margin">The practiſe of <hi>Rich.</hi> the 2. againſt the Duke of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and <hi>Tho. Mowbray</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolke:</hi> For the King feared <hi>Heref.</hi> leaſt (hauing the loue of the people) hee ſhould haue vanquiſht <hi>Mowbray,</hi> and ſo hee baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them both, and leaſt alſo it might haue fallen out that the Duke of <hi>Heref.</hi> ſhould haue gotten the victory, &amp; ſo haue gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced himſelfe.</note> am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious bee neuer permitted to ingage himſelfe in any publique buſineſſe, eſpecially neuer employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Martiall affaires, leaſt by the well managing thereof, he draw vnto himſelfe credit and eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the Common-people, which hee abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, might afterwards turne to the hurt and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the Weale Publique? Or may it bee brought to paſſe by this menes alſo, if diuers of his <note n="u" place="margin">Tholoz. lib. 22.</note> owne ranke and quality do bandy with him, and of ſet purpoſe oppoſe his proceedings, the munition, and all other warlike furniture, being (in the meane time) vnder the command of the Prince, or Common-wealth? Or may this finally be effected, if <note n="x" place="margin">Mach. diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. lib. 1. cap. 52.</note> hinderance be giuen to his ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21030:38"/> deſignes, by the ſame waies, meanes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, which he himſelfe vſed to climbe to the top of his deſires?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may laſtly be demanded, wherefore the more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Cities (as in particular it may truely bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced in, and of, this Honour able Citie of</hi> 
                     <note n="y" place="margin">So <hi>Ia cke Straw</hi> his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion begun in <hi>Kent,</hi> in the time of <hi>Rich.</hi> the 2. who was flame by the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>William Walworth,</hi> in <hi>Smith-field,</hi> whereby the Citie for that honourable ſeruice had the Dagger added to their Armes. So <hi>Iacke Cade</hi> his conſpiracy and rebellion in <hi>Henry</hi> the 6. his daies, came from <hi>Kent</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. So <hi>Kets</hi> conſpiracie came from <hi>Norfolke</hi> in the time of <hi>Edw.</hi> the 6. So the rebellion in the North, was moued againſt Q <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of Famous me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory by impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Pius Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> B. of <hi>Rome.</hi> So the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-treaſon was plotted &amp; contriued in our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord King <hi>Iames</hi> his</note> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don) <hi>are generally free from plotting, practiſing, or contriuing any treaſons, rebellions, inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, mutinies, &amp;c. againſt the Prince, or State: when other more remote parts of the Kingdome, are, and euer haue beene more ſubiect to put in practiſe ſuch helliſh proiects?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it for that in the more famous and eminent Cities (where the Magiſtrates are commonly more carefull and watchfull then other where) the plotters of treaſons and rebellions, cannot ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniently conueene and come to together, to conſult about their villanies, without being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, obſerued, and eſpied, as they may do vnder any colourable pretext, in the Countries neere adioyning, or other remote parts from ſuch Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? Or is it not for this cauſe alone, but for that in ſuch eminent Cities (and in particular within this Citie of <hi>London)</hi> the word of God is more plentifully Preached, whereby the Citizens are better inſtructed in their duties to God and their Prince, then commonly they are in all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie beſides? Or may this bee a further reaſon for the ſaid Citie of <hi>London</hi> in particular, for that as
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:21030:39"/> well the chiefe Magiſtrate thereof, as other wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <note place="margin">time, by diuers Gentlemen in ſeuerall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. But in all theſe there was neuer a Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen in any of them.</note> Citizens therein, are neerer to the Court, and by reaſon of their eminent places, and prime Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which they beare, and daily do execute for the Prince, and in his name, to the good of Towne and Country, haue (euer) more dependance of their Prince, then in other places further diſtant there-from, the other ſubiects can haue: whereby it commeth to paſſe that they neuer deſire inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations, nor engage themſelues and their eſtates by plotting of treaſons, raiſing rebellions, &amp;c. but content themſelues with their owne conditions, ſtudying to loue, and to bee beloued of their Prince, which things are not ſo well performed by particulars, in places further diſtant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, as hath beene ſhewed? Or, to conclude, may this likewiſe be the reaſon, for that the ſaid Citie of <hi>London,</hi> being the <hi>Chamber</hi> of the Prince, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee euer preſumeth that hee may be moſt ſafe, the Citizens euen out of their loue and loyalty to their Prince, haue euer thought foule ſcorne that themſelues ſhould be found vntrue, or diſloyall; or that themſelues, or their Citie ſhould be bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the hatefull name of Traytors, or hauing treaſon, rebellion, or treachery, batched in it?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:21030:39"/>
               <head>SECT. I. CHAP. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Studies, diſpoſitions, &amp; whence the diuerſitie thereof may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed: Of Learning likewiſe, knowledge of tongues and Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, how neceſſary &amp; auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able they are in generall, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially for a Prince, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he may more cleerly ſee, and exactly iudge of his owne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires. Of Intelligence, and the vſe and benefit thereof.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may be demanded, whence the varieties of ſtudies and diuerſity of diſpoſitions of men might proceed?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Oth this diuerſity happen by <note n="a" place="margin">Fran. Guicch.</note> reaſon of the varietie of times and places? Or not ſo neither, but by the mutabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the vnſtable multitude rather, of whom this Prouerbe is truly veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, <hi>So many men, ſo many mindes?</hi> Or falleth it out
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21030:40"/> thus the rather, by reaſon of the <note n="b" place="margin">Tholozanus.</note> difference of yeares, and vnlikeneſſe of manners of the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of one and the ſelfe-ſame kingdome, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and ends of the Nobles, Senators, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, being cleane contrary one to the other?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, wherefore wiſe men haue in all ages greatly indeuoured to perſwade all men to get learning and knowledge before any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>WAs it becauſe they plainly ſaw and percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that it was the beſt meanes <note n="c" place="margin">Sen. Epiſt. 98.</note> to purge and purifie the mindes of men, whereby they might bee apted to receiue and retaine ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous precepts? Or might this be the reaſon, for that they well knew, that the embracing of good letters was <note n="d" place="margin">Quintilian, lib. 12.</note> the high-way to wiſedome, by which the policie of a State is moſt aduanced?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, wherefore the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and skill of languages is neceſſary and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for all men, but eſpecially for a Prince and priuy Councellour?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>MAy this be the reaſon, for that all men are commonly well pleaſed to <note n="e" place="margin">Guicch.</note> vnderſtand, &amp; to be vnderſtood of thoſe with whom they ſhall chaunce to haue any dealing? Or may this be the cauſe, for that a man being skilfull in the tongues, can <note n="f" place="margin">Cominaeus.</note> better explaine himſelfe and his
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:21030:40"/> owne meaning, and ſhall much better bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, then if he ſhould deale by an Interpretor? Or may this likewiſe be a maine reaſon, for that many times it falleth out, that a priuy Councellor is to take notice of ſome ſerious buſineſſes, which mightily import the State to know, and bee ſecret in, which things can neuer be related, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted ſo well, nor to ſuch good purpoſe, if for want of knowledge of the tongues, the Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor or Relator muſt of neceſſity vſe the helpe of ſome third perſon? Or may the knowledge of tongues bee thought ſo auaileable to a Prince or Stateſman, for the entertaining and giuing au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Embaſſadors, hearing of their meſſages, be they hoſtile or friendly, and giuing them their diſpatches, anſweres, and diſmiſſions?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, wherefore wiſe men haue held the knowledge of Hiſtories to be the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt way whereby a man may become wiſe, calling</hi> 
                     <note n="g" place="margin">Tacit. 4. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Cic. de Orator. Diodorus Sicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus. Cominaeus.</note> 
                     <hi>Hiſtory the life and ſoule of memory, the light of truth, director of mans life, &amp;c?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it becauſe that by reading of Hiſtories, a man ſhall truely find <note n="h" place="margin">Diod. Sicul. 1. Bibliorum.</note> 
                     <hi>Vertue,</hi> to haue her due praiſe, and honour giuen her, as contrariwiſe to <hi>Vice,</hi> her due ſhame and reproofe? Or may this bee the reaſon, for that <note n="i" place="margin">Plutarchus. in Timol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>onte.</note> Hiſtory is auialeable to inſtruct any priuate man (of what degree ſoeuer) how to flame his life, and carry himſelfe with commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in the eye of the world, when, as in a glaſſe,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:21030:41"/> he ſhall ſee how to beautifie &amp; compoſe it, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the patterne of other mens vertues? Or may this bee a further reaſon, for that thereby a man may <note n="k" place="margin">Liuy lib.</note> become a Stateſman, and know how to manage publique affaires, drawing his rules and directions out of old Antiquities, and times paſſed, as out of a Store-houſe, and making ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication thereof to the time preſent?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, what may be the chiefe vſe, benefit and end of Intelligence?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>MAy it be beneficiall to a Prince or State, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he may thereby <note n="l" place="margin">Fran. Guicch. Aul. Pol.</note> diſtinctly know the condition and ſtate of all Countries, the power and ſtrength of their Princes and Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, the wiſedome and skilfulneſſe of their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators, in managing the affaires of State, and the originals and continuance of their families, with many other particulars neceſſary to bee knowne to a Prince or State, who either hath, or may haue dealing with other Nations? Or may this rather be the chiefe vſe &amp; end of Intelligence, that a Prince or wiſe Stateſman may thereby bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note n="m" place="margin">Polib. lib. 1. Pacuvius &amp; Guich.</note> diſcouer the ſecret fraudes, and cunning practiſes of his faire tongued, and ſmooth-faced friends (but indeed his craftie and ſubtile ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries) as likewiſe the machinations, drifts, and intents of his open enemies, whereby he may better be enabled to explicate and winde himſelfe out of dangers, or fruſtrate their intentions, by croſſing and counter-mining of them?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:21030:41"/>
               <head>SECT. I. CHAP. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of peace, and the conditions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: Of the State, and affaires of Princes: Of Embaſſages, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, and who are fitteſt to vndertake ſuch charge: what Arguments are moſt perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue, and of the great vſe of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qence in a Stateſ-man or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may bee demanded, why wiſe-men haue alwaies thought peace to be expedient for both parties, as well for the victor, as thoſe who haue beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>IGHT it bee for this reaſon, for that they ſuppoſed it <note n="a" place="margin">Senec. Here. Fur.</note> impoſſible for the world to continue, if it ſhould bee vexed with continuall wars? Or might this rather be the reaſon, for that they truely iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged that the <note n="b" place="margin">Idem Ibidem,</note> conquered muſt of neceſſity, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:21030:42"/> of what peace and conditions ſoeuer the Victor ſhall grant them? And that they thought it likewiſe to bee a <note n="c" place="margin">Liu. lib. 30.</note> comely and gracefull thing to the conquerour, to affoord them peace vpon rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable termes, that all men might take notice, that hee knew how to begin, and ingage himſelfe in a iuſt warre, and was able likewiſe to make an end thereof? Or might not this be the onely rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but for that they thought it <note n="d" place="margin">Tacit. Annal. lib. 12.</note> profitable like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and ſafe for the Conquerour to lay downe his Armes, conſidering that if hee ſhould ſtill proſecute the warres, hee ſhould reape nothing but weariſomeneſſe by continuing and protract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, and if hee ſhould make too much haſt, and as it were inforce an end of them, hee might runne himſelfe into many and <note n="e" place="margin">Henr. Ranſov. de re Bellica.</note> needleſſe dangers, euen to the hazard of his owne eſtate, which otherwiſe hee might eaſily haue auoyded? For Fortune will ſometimes play the Iade, and the euent of warres is vncertaine?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, how a ſafe and firme peace, may bee diſtinguiſhed and knowne from that which is vnſure and not to be truſted vnto?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>MAy this be knowne, if the peace bee <note n="f" place="margin">Liu. lib. 25.</note> honeſt, as putting an end to the warres, by giuing and accepting of tollerable conditions? Or may it this may be knowne likewiſe, if it bee <note n="g" place="margin">Tacit. 4. Hist.</note> ſimple, plaine, and without falſe colours or gloſſes, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buiguity of words, or equiuocations, and not
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:21030:42"/> ſubiect to what conſtructions the peace-breaker may wreſt or draw them?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, why that Prince who came to his Kingdome by ſome of the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or Senate, ſhall more hardly keepe it, then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who obtained the Crowne by the ſuffrages and aſsiſtance of the people?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it becauſe that <note n="h" place="margin">Mach. Prin. cap. 9.</note> thoſe of the Nobility thinke themſelues to be little inferiour, or rather equall with the Prince, whereupon hee cannot ſway the Scepter as him liſteth, but muſt bee glad in the moſt things to be ruled by them? Or may this ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bee the reaſon, for that it will bee thought the Prince will <note n="i" place="margin">So fared it with the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> in the time of <hi>Richard</hi> the 3. with <hi>Charles</hi> the 8. and <hi>Lewis</hi> the 12. Kings of <hi>France,</hi> in the loſſe of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane, &amp;c.</hi> as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth <hi>Mach. Prin. Cap. 9.</hi>
                     </note> neuer be able ſufficiently to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thoſe Nobles, without the hurt and wronging of others, which when hee cannot, thoſe very men, by whoſe aide and aſſiſtance hee got the Crowne, will bee the firſt who will pull him downe againe? Or may this be the reaſon, for that <note n="k" place="margin">Idem Ibidem.</note> if the Commons ſhould make head againſt the Prince, hee could neuer bee ſecured of his ſafety, or retayning of his Kingdome, becauſe they would oppreſſe him with multitude, the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty being but a handfull to them?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:21030:43"/>
                  <head>4</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, wherefore it ſo much importeth a Prince to manage his Martiall affaires in his owne perſon, if hee euer looke to grow fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous by his conqueſts?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it becauſe it <note n="1" place="margin">
                        <hi>Quint. Curt. Mach. Prin.</hi> So <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand</hi> King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Hen.</hi> the 5. King of <hi>Eng.</hi> became famous.</note> ſo much encreaſeth and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth his eſtimation, and credit with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Princes abroad, and breedeth and beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him loue and authority among his owne peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at home? Or may this be the reaſon, for that by this meanes, all <note n="m" place="margin">Mach. diſput. lib. 1. cap. 30.</note> wrangling occaſions, and heart-burnings are cut off, whereby a Prince ſometimes proueth vngratefull to men, euen of the beſt deſerts? For when Princes preſent, and behaue themſelues brauely in the field, all the honour and glory thereof (as it pertaineth) ſo it redoundeth vnto them: whereas otherwiſe if they were abſent, and committed the managing of thoſe affaires to their Generals, they ſtraight waies imagine, that if their forces ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, the glory of the day ſhould reſt with the Generall, who led the Army, and that themſelues can neuer challenge any part of the victory, got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, vnleſſe they extinguiſh the merites of the Generall, or himſelfe, and by that meanes proue vniuſt and vngratefull to their ſeruants.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:21030:43"/>
                  <head>5</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, how a Courtier may come to bee much imployed in his Princes affaires?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>MAy he effect this, if he <note n="n" place="margin">Guicch.</note> ſhould waite dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, and bee alwaies in the eye of the Prince? Or may hee compaſſe this the rather, if once imployed hee manage that affaire well? For by this meanes, hee ſhall both gaine himſelfe reputation, and bee thought fit and able to deale in any buſineſſe, and be ſure (almoſt) neuer to be out of action, by reaſon of the dependencies which other buſineſſes haue vpon thoſe, wherein hee formerly hath beene employed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſidering that by well or ill managing and handling of the affaires of Princes, in negotiating for them with forreigne Princes, either great good, or great hurt may accrew to the Prince and State, it may be demanded what manner of men a Prince might chiefly imploy for Embaſſadours to forreigne Princes?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>SHall hee vſe ſuch as are <note n="o" place="margin">Comineus.</note> skilfull to picke and gleane ſomething out of other mens employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and appropriate it to themſelues, if there bee hope that their credit and eſtimation, may grow greater by it? Or ſhall not a Prince truſt to ſuch to negotiate for him, but to thoſe rather, who are faithfull, carefull, meeke, and gentle, and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:21030:44"/> haue beene long practiſed and experienced in managing ſuch affaires?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further be demanded, with what tooles an Ambaſſadour ſhall ſooneſt perſwade a forreigne Prince, and draw him to fauour, and further his maiſters deſignes?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>SHall he aſſaile him with <note n="p" place="margin">Tholoz.</note> firme arguments and ſound reaſons? But hee that is nice, and hath a ſpeciall opinion of his owne wiſedome, will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently diſtaſt that or any thing that is ſolide. Or ſhall he rather ſet vpon him with <note n="q" place="margin">Fran. Guicch. Cominaeus. Mach. Prin.</note> repreſentations of colours, Popularities, and circumſtances? And (to ſpeake as the truth is) theſe are of no leſſe (if they bee not of more) force, then firme and ſound reaſons: For circumſtances, colours, repreſentations, and ſuch like ſtuffe, are of ſuch power and efficacy, that they can giue life to true and ſound reaſons, peruert the iudgement, if it bee not ſtable and well grounded, and quickly leade into errour.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, why eloquence is ſo neceſſary for a Councellour, or an Embaſſador?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IS it becauſe that daily amoſt it falleth out, that a Prince hath occaſion to ſend ſome one or
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:21030:44"/> other of his Councell to forreigne States, either to perſwade; to accuſe, or defend; to gratulate, or condole, &amp;c. Now it is both requiſite, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and commodious for a Prince to bee furniſhed with men ſo qualified, with eloquence, vtterance, &amp;c. as that they may with credit to him and his Court, well diſcharge the place, and perſon they ſuſtaine; And it ſhould be a great ſhame, diſaduantageous, and diſhonourable to the Prince, if for want of ſuch gifts, in any whom hee ſhould ſend on ſuch errands, it ſhould fall out otherwiſe. Or may it rather be for this cauſe; for that in <note n="r" place="margin">Quintilian.</note> pacifying ſuch as are ſeditious in the State, and compounding the quarrels and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of ſuch as are factious, there is no better meane to accord them, then to vſe an eloquent and plauſible ſpeech vnto them?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:21030:45"/>
               <head>SECT. I. CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Diſcord and Faction, whereof they take their beginnings, and of the nouriſhing, or not nouriſhing of them in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may bee demanded from whence diſcords and factions haue their beginnings?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>OE they ariſe of ſuch <note n="a" place="margin">Tholoz. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. lib. 22.</note> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as are ſodainely ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted to the people, ſo that there cannot bee time giuen them to thinke or conſider what matter they go about? Or do they take their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings rather of <note n="b" place="margin">Idem Ibidem.</note> the priuate or open hatred of Familiers? Or may they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed rather from the roote of <note n="c" place="margin">Senec. Epiſt. 74</note> pride and ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whilſt euery man ſtriueth to proceed, and go
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:21030:45"/> before another, and is alwaies detracting from him hee liketh not? Or may they haue their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings from idleneſſe and looſeneſſe of liuing, which oftentimes are wont to miniſter occaſions of ciuill (or rather vnciuill) brawles and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions? Or may they ariſe of the <note n="d" place="margin">Tholoz. de Re pub. lib. 22.</note> different mindes and diſpoſitions of the people, from the deſignes and intentions of the Nobility? Or not ſo much from thence neither, but of the waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring mutability of the vnconſtant multitude alſo? their years being ſo diuers, and their manners ſo vnlike: For it is impoſſible, that where there is ſuch and ſo great diuerſity of yeares, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parity of manners, that the multitude or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons altogether, ſhould equally well like of, affect, and comport the preſent State, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywiſe diſagree, grow factious, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, whether it may bee beneficiall to a Prince or State to nouriſh factions, or no?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IT were too hard a taske for mee <hi>(Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable)</hi> to take vpon mee difinitiuely to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine this queſtion: for I am not ignorant that amongſt diuers men, and thoſe of the wiſeſt ſort, this doubt hath beene canuaſed, and greatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerted; yet ſeeing that I am entred into it, I thought it not fit altogether to paſſe it ouer in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:21030:46"/> without ſhewing your <hi>Honour</hi> my priuate opinion therein, which that I may do the better, I will rip vp the Arguments on both ſides. That factions (therefore) ſhould bee nouriſhed of a Prince or State, many things may induce and perſwade thereunto, but eſpecially theſe two, <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Profit.</hi> For that <hi>Prince</hi> 
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Mach. Prin. cap. 20.</note> muſt needes bee honoured and feared, who alwaies hath an enemy at his owne deuotion, and neuer reſiſting his deſignes and enterpriſes: For hee that can conquer when hee liſt, is not onely admired, but much feared likewiſe, both at home and abroad. For all men with one voyce will giue it out, that hee got the victory by his owne valour and proweſſe: Which ſo reported and beleeued, there is no doubt but that hee ſhall bee much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed therefore, though he atchieued it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; namely, by being ſeconded with a potent faction, ioyning with him againſt their owne Prince, or otherwiſe. Againe, that the chiefeſt and moſt potent Cities of a Kingdome, ſhould be brought vnder the Princes ſubiection, it were not onely conducible and neceſſary, but alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, both to him and the common-wealth. Now to effect this, a Prince muſt either vſe force or policy. If hee ſay to compaſſe his deſignes by force, hee muſt of neceſſity offer many iniuries to the people, which the more openly they are done, the more they do prouoke them to miſlike the Prince: For that which the Law hath made Mine, and Thine, if it ſhould be ſnatched away
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:21030:46"/> from the Subiect, it would bee grieuouſly taken, and held for no better then an intollerable peece of iniuſtice. But when the <note n="f" place="margin">Mach. diſ. lib. 2. cap. 25.</note> Cities of themſelues are become factious, and the Citizens doe waſte and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nſume themſelues by quarrels and facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the fault ſhall neuer bee laid on the Prince, but on the factious, and yet by this meanes the Prince in effect, ſhall obtaine what hee deſired. For the Cities hereby growing weake, and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with continuall garboiles, will willingly put themſelues into the Princes protection, and yeeld themſelues ſubiect to his will. Further, for a Prince to diuert the current of the warres, or any hoſtile inuaſions, from his owne dores, it is very neceſſary, behouefull and conuenient: Now it is not incredible, that euer hee ſhall haue any better way, or meane to bring this to paſſe, then by <note n="g" place="margin">Herod. lib. 4. Xenoph. de Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia Cyri. lib. 3.</note> nouriſhing factions, and diſſentions in his enemies Countrie; for many haue put this in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe heretofore, and greatly thriuen thereby: Moreouer diuers of the wiſeſt ſort, haue thought it very aduantageous to the Prince, that the <note n="h" place="margin">Tacit. Agric.</note> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects ſhould neuer come altogether, to conſult, or agree altogether, vpon any thing which might tend to their common or particular ſafeties. To conclude, <note n="i" place="margin">Tholoz. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. lib. 23.</note> that a great Prince, or Monarch, may become more wary of his enemy, and better conſerue his owne eſtate, it hath beene thought fit, by ſome of the wiſeſt heads that euer haue beene, that ſuch a Prince ſhould neuer bee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an enemy, or be a great nouriſher of facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:21030:47"/> in a forreigne Land: Which courſe, if <hi>Rome</hi> had taken, and not deſtroyed <hi>Carthage,</hi> they ſhould haue had their braue ſpirited youth better trayned vp, practiſed, and made ready in feates of Armes, which might haue ſteeded the Common-wealth for offence or defence thereof; Graue and mature counſell ſhould haue flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the Senate, the Citizens ſhould not haue waſted themſelues with ciuill warres, and ſo the Empire ſhould haue beene more durable and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting. The reaſons of thoſe who hold it vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and euery way diſaduantageous to a Prince, to nouriſh factions, are as follow. It is <note n="k" place="margin">Mach. lib. 3. diſ. cap. 37.</note> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, ſay they, by reaſon of an inbred incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy in the nature of men, that thoſe factions, which at this, or that preſent, depend vpon a Prince, ſhould alwaies, and after one and the ſelfe-ſame manner, bee ſo affected towards him, for that men being wauering, doe greatly deſire ſometimes this Prince, ſometimes that Prince, to be their chiefe Patron. Againe, <note n="l" place="margin">Idem Ibidem.</note> the nourſhing of factions, by a Prince in a forreigne Land, is oftentimes the cauſe, that by little and little, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords and ciuill garboyles are brought into his owne Country, which will ſcarcely be thought to bee conuenient. Further, a great inconuenience, or rather an apparant loſſe might happen to a Prince, who ſhould nouriſh factions within his owne Dominions; For <note n="m" place="margin">Idem Prin. cap. 20.</note> vpon any ſodaine inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſuch Cities of his, which ſhould happen to bee rent aſunder by factions, muſt of neceſſity
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:21030:47"/> be all loſt: For the <note n="n" place="margin">Tholoz. lib. de Repub. 23.</note> weaker part would rather ſubmit, and apply it ſelfe to a ſtranger, then yeeld to the aduerſe faction in any thing. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer this courſe of gouerning, by nouriſhing of factions, muſt needs <note n="o" place="margin">Mach. Prin. cap. 20.</note> argue the weakeneſſe, and imbecility of the Prince, both in power and iudgement: For if hee were ſtrong and prudent, hee would neuer indure that his Country ſhould bee torne in peeces by factions and contentions. To conclude, ſeeing that euery faction conſiſteth of few or many, both of theſe muſt needs bee hurtfull to the Common-wealth: This latter for that <note n="p" place="margin">Liu. lib. 34.</note> they truſting to their owne ſtrength, would preſently take Armes, and turne the quiet of the State into garboiles: The former likewiſe, though perhaps ſomewhat more ſecretly and ſlowly, would no leſſe vexe and moleſt the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, by reaſon that <note n="q" place="margin">Ariſt. 5. Polit. cap. 4.</note> factions of the Nobility are wont to draw vnto themſelues all, or the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of the Commons, to take part with ſuch or ſuch of them, as they moſt affect. Theſe things thus ſtanding, they conclude, that factions are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bee extinguiſhed and quenched, then nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed. For mine owne part <hi>(Right Honourable)</hi> though I will determine nothing of this matter, yet thus I thinke thereof. That Factions, to the ſingular benefite of the Prince, and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, may be nouriſhed in a forreigne gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and though it were not ſo conuenient (perhaps) they ſhould bee ſet on foote, and maintained at home, yet at no hand are they to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:21030:48"/> be neglected, eſpecially in the time of peace. For ſeeing that there is no Common-wealth, which doth not breed and bring forth, yea foſter and cheriſh ſome enuy and contention: theſe contentions may proue healthfull to the State of a Common-wealth, as Agues are ſometime be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall to the ſtate of a mans body: And it is certaine that the <hi>Romane</hi> Common-wealth, was neuer in better health and ſafety, then when the <hi>Tribunes</hi> of the People, and the <hi>Patricians</hi> were at variance: and the <hi>Lacedaemonian</hi> State ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in better ſtate, then when their <hi>Ephori,</hi> and their Kings could not agree. For by this cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of one another, the publique Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a Common-wealth were better diſcharged, both at home and abroad.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:21030:48"/>
               <head>SECT. I. CHAP. XIIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Sedition, Mutiny, and defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of the greateſt part of the people in a State, and of ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Newtrall,</hi> or part taking.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may be demanded whence ſedition and muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, in, or, againſt a State taketh his beginning?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>AY it ariſe and ſpring out of the bitter <note n="a" place="margin">Tholoz. Ariſtotle 5. Pol. Cap. 3.</note> roote of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, as when men ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the remedy of preſent euils and dangers, to bee the euils and dangers themſelues, doe vpon a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine breake out, and ſo take Armes? Or may it proceede <note n="b" place="margin">Idem Ibidem.</note> of feare as the Phyloſopher well conceited? For feare may moue and incite men, to bee ſeditious, fearing or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting puniſhments to be inflicted vpon them, for the wrongs they haue done, and by this
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:21030:49"/> meanes running out, they thinke (or at leaſt are willing) to preuent them before they can bee put in execution. Or may this proceed of too much indulgency, clemency, and remiſſneſſe of the gouernement, together with the ſuperfluity and aboundance of all things, it being rather the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the people to <note n="c" place="margin">Liuy lib. 2.</note> grow to bee Wantons then Warriours? Or may it come rather of <note n="d" place="margin">Saluſt. Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurth.</note> penury, and ſcarcity of things neceſſary? Or may it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen through the <note n="e" place="margin">Liu. lib. 38.</note> pride and ambition of euill Gouernours and Councellours? Or may it rather ariſe of taking vp too much mony at Vſe, with the which the Commons being (as it were) eaten vp, and their ſtates conſumed, they grow deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate thereupon, and ſo take Armes, thinking <note n="f" place="margin">Tacit. 1. Hist.</note> themſelues moſt ſafe when they runne the moſt vncertaine courſes? for worſe then they are, they thinke they cannot bee.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It may further bee demanded, whether, when once ſedition groweth hot, and commeth to Heads, it were better to ſtand Newtrall, then to fall to part-taking?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TOuching this Queſtion <hi>(Right Honourable)</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe that <note n="g" place="margin">Solon.</note> great <hi>Athenian Law-giuer,</hi> had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed and eſtabliſhed by Law, that vpon any ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ariſing in that State, <note n="h" place="margin">Sic refert A. Gaellius. in Noct. Attic. lib. 2. cap. 12.</note> he that would not take part with one ſide, ſhould bee baniſhed the Citie, and looſe all that euer hee poſſeſſed; I ſhould ſcarce haue thought it worth the looking
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:21030:49"/> into: but after ſo wiſe a man had determined it, and for that I perceiued others, who thought themſelues as wiſe, as the ſaid <hi>Law giuer,</hi> did ſtiffely ſtand againſt his opinion, and vpon good grounds (as they ſuppoſe) produced arguments to the contrary, I thought it worthy my labour likewiſe, to put downe the reaſons on both ſides, and in concluſion to enterpone mine own priuate opinion touching the premiſſes. Thoſe therefore who ſtand on <hi>Solons</hi> ſide, and allow and ſtand for part-taking doe thus argue: <note n="i" place="margin">A. Gaellius noct. Attic. lib. 2. cap. 12.</note> If the good men, which be in the Citie or Common-wealth, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the <hi>Seditious</hi> to bee madded with fury, and to grow to an head, ſhould apply themſelues to either part, there is no doubt, but that they might bee a meanes to reduce them to vnity; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading firſt with their owne ſide, how ill beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a thing it is, for Citizen to ſtriue with, or take Armes againſt Citizen, and what deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them and theirs may enſue, if they ſuffer themſelues ſtill to be led with paſſion, and by that meanes mollifying their owne friends minds, they may (happily) get leaue likewiſe to deale with the other ſide, in thoſe or ſuch like termes, and ſo perſwade both parties to lay downe their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons. Againe, <note n="k" place="margin">Phauorinus Philoſophus.</note> thoſe which take part with nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, if the differences of the factious ſhould once bee compounded, ſhould ſmart for it, being hated on both ſides, deemed as pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique enemies, and ſuch as ſolaced themſelues, and reioyced to ſee them at thoſe oddes, and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:21030:50"/> therefore are iuſtly expoſed to the prey, and iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of either party. Further, it were very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous when the Citie or Common-wealth is diuided into faction, not to take part with the one or the other ſide, leaſt a <note n="l" place="margin">Ioſephus de bello Iudaico.</note> third faction ſhould ſpring out of the others, as hath ſometimes beene read to haue falne out in the Iewes Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. But thoſe which ſtand for newtrality, think otherwiſe, and thus they reaſon <note n="m" place="margin">Tacit. Annal.</note> Ciuill Armes of themſelues, can neither be prouided, taken vp, or managed by any good or lawfull meanes, and the iſſue and end of them commonly proueth naught. For the Leaders and Captaines of the ſeditious, vnder the pretence of ſeeking the good of the Common wealth, do euery one ſeeke to promote his owne ambitious humours, and ſo draw the people to follow their fancies, which no good Patriote ought to do. Againe, it argueth great fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in any, who ſhal take either part, and ioyne with the ſeditious: for by that meanes they <note n="n" place="margin">Saluſt. in bello Iug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rthino.</note> ſtrengthen and encourage them, encreaſe their malice to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Countrey-men, and fellow-Citizens of the aduerſe partie, and become partakers of their rebellions, madneſſe, and folly. Touching mine owne priuate opinion herein, I think (right Honourable) that newtrality is regularly to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded in either Prince or Courtier, except in ſome maine caſe, where a man by making ſhew to be newtrall, may more handſomly compouud and contriue his owne buſineſſe, and better promote, and ſooner come to his owne ends.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21030:50"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
